So what is data science?
Well, according to O'Reilly, data science
aims to drive knowledge from big data
efficiently and intelligently.
Data science encompasses the set of activities, tools,
and methods that enable data-driven activities
in science, business, medicine, and government.
Here's another definition of data science.
Data science combines three different skills-- hacking
skills, math and statistics knowledge, and domain expertise
skills.
Now this leads to some interesting intersections.
For example, between hacking skills and math and statistics
knowledge, we have traditional machine learning.
So this is the case where you have somebody
who can apply algorithms at scale to large amounts of data,
and understand both the algorithms and the results
that they see from those algorithms.
Combining the skills of math and statistics
knowledge with domain expertise, we have traditional research.
So this is where someone in a specific domain
is able to collect some data, and then
perform detailed analyses on that data,
understanding both the analytical process
and the results that they get.
The danger zone is someone who has hacking skills and domain
expertise skills.
In this case, you have someone who
is able to collect a lot of domain-specific knowledge,
apply algorithms to that at scale,
but doesn't really understand either the algorithms
or the results that they get from applying those algorithms.
So if you remember the cautionary tale
from last time about the Facebook analysis,
that's a case where someone applied hacking skills
to a large amount of domain-specific information,
and yielded a result that they didn't really understand.
The combination of hacking skills, math and statistics
knowledge, and domain expertise yields data science.
Someone who can apply domain-specific knowledge
at very large scale, while understanding
both the algorithms that they're applying,
and the results that they get from applying those algorithms.