One way to understand what data science is
is to contrast it with other domains.
So let's contrast it first with databases.
In databases, every data value is precious
because our data values are things like bank records
or personnel records or census or medical records.
We don't want to lose or corrupt any of that.
In data science, our data is cheap
because it's things like online clicks
or GPS logs or tweets or tree sensor readings.
We can lose a value, and it won't affect our end results.
And this is because in data science, the volume of data
that we have is absolutely massive.
Whereas in databases, it's fairly modest.
Databases have some very important properties;
consistency, error recovery, and auditability.
Consistency means we always want to make sure
that our database has the correct information.
Error recovery means that if the database server fails
or the disk fails, we want to make sure
that we can recover all of the data and not lose any of it.
Auditability means that we want to make
sure we can know who made a change
and when they made that change.
In contrast, the primary properties and priorities
for data science are speed, availability,
and query richness.
We want to get answers as quickly as possible.
We always want our system to be available to give us
those quick answers, and we want to be
able to ask very complex questions.
Now, databases are very strongly structured.
They have a schema that very clearly defines
all of the fields that we store in that database
and the types of those fields.
In data science, we may have no structure,
or it may be very weak structure.
We may simply just have a text file
that contains our information.
Now, databases have very important properties
of transactions and ACID semantics.
Transactions mean that we're able to control how
the database changes its state.
And we do that using the ACID properties.
ACID stands for atomicity, consistency, isolation,
and durability.
Atomicity means that when we make a change in the database,
it happens completely or not at all.
Consistency means our database is always
in a consistent or correct state.
And isolation means that if we have multiple things occurring
within that database at the same time,
they're isolated from one another.
Durability means that once we've made a change to the database,
we guarantee that that change will
survive even if the system should crash or should fail.
In data science, instead we have the properties
like the CAP theorem.
CAP theorem stands for consistency, availability,
and partition tolerance.
The CAP theorem says that we can have any two of those
properties, but we cannot have all three of those properties.
So for example, imagine that we have
two systems that are interconnected and sharing
data.
And we want to make sure that those systems are
consistent with one another because they
have the same data in them.
So they're connected.
Well, if that connection is broken,
then changes made to one of the systems
will not be apparent in the other system.
So if we want to have a system that's consistent overall,
we can't make that system be available and tolerate
partitions.
So you can apply each of these consistency, availability,
and partition tolerance properties and look at them,
and you can only have two of them at the same time.
Can't have all three.
The second aspect of data science
is that we're interested in eventual consistency.
So in these two systems that are the same system
but are distributed, we don't require
that they be perfectly consistent all of the time.
They could be slightly out of sync with one another.
But eventually, they will be consistent.
So as an example, imagine that you have a friend in England,
and you're in the United States.
And you add that person as a friend on Facebook.
Well, Facebook's distributed.
So it means it might take a few seconds
before they notice that they've been added as a friend.
The final property that we want to look
at in contrasting databases is the realizations,
the query languages that we can use.
Databases store their data using the structured query language,
or SQL.
In data science, we store it using NoSQL data stores.
And there are many different open source data stores that
provide the NoSQL environment.
The key properties of the NoSQL environment
is they allow for much more rich queries
than we have in the SQL environment.
Another contrast that we have with databases
is that if you think about it, databases
are all about collecting data and then querying that data.
But that data represents the past.
So we're really querying the past.
Whereas with data science, we collect data,
and then we want to use that to query the future.
So this is very related to business analytics.
Because in business analytics, the goal
is to obtain actionable insight in complex environments.
The challenge that we have, both in data science
and in business analytics, is that we
have vast amounts of disparate, unstructured data,
and we have to provide a result in a very
limited amount of time.
So for example, trying to decide,
do I show someone a particular ad or not.
So I want to know, are they likely to click on that ad?
Are they likely to click on that ad and purchase that product?
Or what related products do I show someone?
Or at a supermarket, what coupon do I print out
when they're checking out?
We can contrast data science with scientific computing.
So here on the left, we have a climate model example
as a case of scientific modeling.
And on the right, we have a system
being developed at Lawrence Berkeley National Labs that's
designed to determine whether a particular image
from a telescope contains a supernova or not.
In scientific modeling, we build physics-based models,
and we use those to derive properties of our data.
In the data driven approach, we build general inference engines
instead of these physics based models.
So here on the right, we have a general purpose machine
learning classifier that's being trained to recognize
images that contain supernovas.
In scientific modeling, everything
is structured around the problem that we're trying to solve,
whereas in a data driven approach,
we're using general purpose or things that
are not related to the structure of the problem.
Scientific modeling is mostly deterministic
and quite precise, whereas in a data driven approach,
we build statistical models that handle this true randomness
and that can deal with unmodeled complexity.
So in the case of the climate model,
we have to understand exactly how particles in the atmosphere
are going to interact.
But in the case of detecting supernovas,
we're simply taking a picture that
contains pixels representing photons
received from a telescope, by a telescope.
So here there's tremendous complexity
in trying to determine whether this image is
an image of a supernovae or not.
Trying to come up with a physics based model to determine that
would be truly a massive undertaking.
Instead, we use a much simpler approach
using these statistical models that
tries to detect whether the supernova is present or not.
And there's going to be a degree of accuracy, or alternatively
inaccuracy, in those results.
Scientific modeling runs on supercomputers or on high end
cluster computers.
These clusters can cost over $1 billion.
In contrast, data science runs on cheaper computer clusters
like Amazon EC2.
We can contrast data science with traditional machine
learning.
In traditional machine learning, it's
all about developing novel individual models,
whereas in data science, we'll explore many models.
We'll build them.
We'll tune them.
We'll build hybrids of models.
They're also considered very inexpensive.
In traditional machine learning, it's
all about proving mathematical properties of the models.
Whereas in data science, we want to understand
the empirical properties of the models.
That is, how do they perform in practice,
both in terms of accuracy and in terms of actual wall clock
time?
How quickly do they run?
In traditional machine learning, we take a small, clean data
set, and that's what we use to validate our results
and build our models.
In data science, we're dealing with massive amounts
of dirty data.
We have no control over what's in the data set
and what's not in the data set in terms of cleanliness.
And so we need tools that can handle this dirty data.
In traditional machine learning, the end result
is publishing a paper.
Whereas in data science, we want to use this to build
systems that can take actions.
So one way to look at data science
is how we can use data science to find data scientists.
So kaggle is a website where people
can upload various types of problems
that they want data scientists to solve.
So here's some examples.
And we can see there's one predicting
West Nile virus in Chicago.
There's another one to predict restaurant revenue.
And data scientists can form teams and then
compete to come up with the best solutions to these problems.
And if they come up with the best solution,
they win a prize, a prize being cash.
Now, most data scientists don't participate in kaggle
because they're trying to win money.
Rather, they participate for the bragging rights
of being able to say they came up with the best
possible algorithm.