so now let's look at how we perform data science.
We'll do this by first looking at the view of three data
science experts-- Jim Gray who was a Turing Award-winning
database researcher, Ben Fry who is a data visualization expert,
and Jeff Hammerbacher, who's a former Facebook chief
scientists and Cloudera co-founder.
Then we'll look at cloud computing, which has
become a data science enabler.
So recall that we had this definition of data science.
It combines hacking skills along with math and statistics
knowledge along with domain expertise.
So let's start with Jim Gray's model.
His model is that you capture data, then curate that data,
and then you communicate the results.
So Ben Fry's model takes this down a level of granularity.
Ben Fry starts by first acquiring data, then parsing
that data, then filtering the data,
mining the data for information, representing the results,
refining the model, and then interacting with the results.
Jeff Hammerbacher takes this even a level further.
He starts first by identifying a problem,
instrumenting the data sources, then collecting the data
and then preparing that data.
And that involves integrating the data,
transforming it, cleaning it, filtering it,
and aggregating it.
And then he builds a model.
He then evaluates that model and then communicates the results.
So in each of these cases, you can
see how we start with a problem, we collect data,
we clean that data, build a model,
and then we communicate the results.