Cloud computing is a key enabler of data science.
Instead of going out and purchasing your own computers,
and then having to pay to operate those computers
and maintain them, with Cloud computing,
you rent computers from a Cloud computing provider.
This allows you to reduce overall computing costs,
and in particular, your operating costs for computing.
Cloud computing enables you to perform data science
on a massive scale, because you can
rent huge numbers of inexpensive computers,
perform a problem, exploration, and then
shut down those computers and stop paying for them.
Now to make this possible, Cloud computing providers are
building massive data centers, data
centers that have hundreds of thousands,
or even a million servers in them.
Now there are many challenges to building a data center
that contains a million servers, including cooling,
the building itself, and power, and how you actually organize
the computers into modules.
But people are performing research exactly in engineering
and how to build these things.
And they are building these data centers.
This is driving down the cost of Cloud computing.