So let's focus on the hacking skills portion of what we think
is data science.
The big picture here is that we have many different data
sources.
Like here on the left, we have an application database,
we have files, we have logs.
And we want to get that into our data warehouse,
where we can perform data science
and generate our data products, business
intelligence, and analytics.
This process of getting our raw data into our data warehouse
is called ETL, or extract, transform, and load.
The data acquisition preparation process, this ETL process,
consists of extracting data from some sources,
loading data into a sink, and transforming that data
either at the source, sink, or in some staging area.
Now sources include things like files, databases, logs,
websites, distributed file systems.
And sinks include things like languages, evaluation
and analysis environments, data stores, files, distributed file
systems, and databases.
Data acquisition and preparation consists of multiple phases.
We have to characterize the data,
then we have to clean the data, and then
we have to integrate the data into our system
and along with existing data that we have.
We have to do this very efficiently
in terms of space and time.
That is, for transferring the data
from one source or sink or preparation point to another,
that process involves serializing and deserializing
the data.
When we read it from a file into memory,
that's a very expensive operation.
The same for writing it back to a file,
and the same for reading it in from the network,
or writing it out to the network.
Now we create pipelines, or workflows,
that consist of many stages.
So here's a transformation pipeline
that takes us from a data science file that
contains a bunch of information, to a mail message that
contains a count of the characters, words,
and lines in that file.
We do this using a set of Unix pipes and filters.
So we start by concatenating the file.
We pipe it into the word count program.
The word count program determines the characters,
the words, and the lines, and then we pipe that result
into the mail program which sends a message to someone
with the subject, word count.
Now if we're using this workflow more than once,
we can schedule it.
And that scheduling could either be
done time-based or event-based.
So every hour, we could run this pipeline.
Or we could only run the pipeline
when someone updates the data science file.
Another alternative is to use a publish-subscribe model
to register interest.
So for example, a Twitter feed is where
we do something like that.
You subscribe or follow someone, and then
you only get updates when they make changes,
when they post content.
Now recording the execution of a workflow
is known as capturing its lineage or provenance.
So given this workflow that I have here,
anybody can now take this workflow
and determine the words in a file
and have that mailed to someone.
Now Spark's Resilient Distributed Data
sets capture this lineage for you automatically.
And we'll learn more about that next week.
There are many impediments to collaboration.
The diversity of tools and programming and scripting
languages that we have makes it very hard to share.
I use Python, you use Java.
How do we share a Python script with someone who uses Java?
It's not very easy to do that.
Also it's very difficult, sometimes,
to find a script or a result that someone else has already
computed.
It's much simpler to just write the program from scratch.
So an interesting question is, how could we fix this problem?
Create a library or repository where
we could store these scripts and store these results,
and make it very easy for people to search and find
a particular script or result.
But complicating this, really, is the view
that most analysis work that we do is throw-away.
We do it once and never again.
But that's not really true.
Oftentimes you'll perform an analysis,
then six months later, you'll want
to perform the same analysis to see how things have changed.
What do you do?
You write the script from scratch all over again.
Not really a very good approach.