So what does a data scientist do in practice?
Well, first, they start by digging around in data,
trying to find interesting data to analyze.
And that's why I have a picture here of some kids panning
for gold, trying to find those little nuggets in a lot of dirt
and dirty water.
So the next step is that they have
to clean and prepare that data.
And then they hypothesize a model.
So they think about what they think
might be some interesting properties of the data
and build a model.
They then evaluate and interpret the results of that model.
And oftentimes, you don't get what you expected.
And so you have to go back and collect more data
and repeat the cycle of cleaning, preparing that data,
hypothesizing a new model or maybe a hybrid of your old
and new or some composite model, and then evaluate and interpret
the results from that, and then repeat, and repeat, and repeat.
Until finally, you have a model that you
think gives you interesting statistically
significant results.
And then you want to run that model at massive scale.
And so this is where large scale exploitation comes into play.
Now, some of the topics for data scientists
include data acquisition, data preparation, analysis,
data presentation, data products, and observation
and experimentation.
Now, what makes data science difficult?
Many things.
First, we have to overcome assumptions
and making ad hoc explanations of data patterns.
And this is just human nature.
When we see something, we immediately see a pattern.
It's very hard for us to overcome that pattern
that we saw and really understand,
was that just something sort of like an optical illusion,
or was it really a significant pattern?
We also have to be very careful about just, well,
we think it might be this because.
Those kind of ad hoc explanations
aren't scientifically valid.
We also have to make sure we check,
and we check, and we check again.
We need to validate our models, validate
the integrity of our data pipeline, and so on.
So think about the Google Flu Trends results.
Initially, they had a very accurate model.
But over time, the model became very inaccurate.
And this is because the underlying conditions
changed, flu stories appearing on Google News.
They had to go back and revalidate their models
and revalidate their data pipeline.
And then they got great results again.
We also have to be very careful about overgeneralizing,
that is taking a model and trying to apply it everywhere.
Another hard thing for data science
is communicating our results.
How do you convey the results of your model
to someone who's not a domain expert
or who does not understand statistical methods?
And related to this is we have to make sure that we use
statistical tests correctly.
Again, think about the caveat example
with Facebook, where the researchers did not correctly
apply statistical techniques.
Another challenge is moving from a prototype
model into something that you can run in production
and can actually handle massive amounts of data
and deliver results nearly instantaneously.
And finally, data pipelines can be very complex,
lots of moving parts for many different projects and sources.
And so when something goes wrong, who do you ask for help?