Let's look at four data science roles.
Two are individual.
A businessperson and programmer.
And two are organizational.
An enterprise and a web company.
A businessperson has data sources
that include things like web pages and Excel spreadsheets.
Their ETL process is copy and paste between these documents.
Their data warehouse is often a set of Excel spreadsheets.
And for business intelligence and analytics
they use things like Excel functions, Excel charts,
and Visual Basic.
A programmer has data sources that include web scraping, web
services APIs, Excel spreadsheets
that are exported as comma separated values,
and database queries.
Their ETL consists of lots of scripts,
like Wget, curl, Beautiful Soup, and lxml.
They store their data in flat files.
And their business intelligence and analytics
is tools, like Numpy and Matplotlib,
R, Matlab, and Octave.
The enterprise has data sources that
include application databases, internet files, and application
server log files.
Their ETL is done using commercial products.
And their data warehousing is also
done using commercial products.
And for business intelligence and analytics
they also use a variety of commercial and open source
products.
The web company has its data sources, application databases,
logs drawn from their services tier, and web crawl data.
Their ETL is a set of open source tools,
like Apaches Flume, Sqoop, Pig, Oozie, and Crunch projects.
Their data warehouse is also open source projects
from Apache, things like Hadoop, Hive, Spark, and Spark SQL.
Their business intelligence and analytics
is done using custom dashboards, like Oracle Argus and Razorflow
or open source tools, like R.