One of the most important considerations for file format
is performance.
Now, when you think about file format in terms of performance,
consider the read versus the write performance;
the performance for plain text versus binary format;
the environment that you use, Python versus Scala or Java;
and uncompressed versus compressed.
So here's an example using a 626-megabyte text file
and a 787-megabyte binary file in two environments,
a Python environment using Pandas and a Scala/Java
environment.
Now, on the first line, we see the Python performance.
And we can see that the read time
for the text version of the file, for a text file
is 36 seconds.
The write time is 45 seconds.
There's no times for binary reading of the binary file
because Pandas does not have a binary file I/O library, which
means that the performance that you're going to see for Python
will depend on which particular library that you choose to use.
Now, for Scala and Java, we see that the read time
is 18 seconds.
And the write time is 21 seconds for the text file.
And the read time is one to six seconds for the binary file
and one to six seconds for the write of the binary file.
Now, the difference here in range from one to six seconds
is because six seconds is the time for when we're
doing sustained reading and writing of a file, when it's
not cached in a system cache.
But if it gets cached in the system cache,
we'll see much faster performance, especially when
dealing with binary files.
Now overall, we can see that the read and write
times are quite comparable between Python
and also for Scala and Java.
However, we notice that binary I/O is much,
much faster than text I/O. In fact, it's
more than an order of magnitude greater performance
when dealing with binary files instead of textual files.