Working with tabular data introduces several challenges.
The format may not be well defined.
It may be missing data values.
Types may be incorrectly inferred.
So for example, if a cell contains 2, instead of 2.0,
the type might incorrectly be inferred as integer.
And then there's no support for versioning of the format,
and many other challenges that you'll have to face.
When you have tabular data from multiple sources,
there are additional challenges that you may face.
Not every source may provide the same data,
which means that some fields may be missing.
There may be inconsistent data types
between the different sources.
So one file may have dollar values,
while another file has pound values.
There also may be inconsistent values for the same entity.
One file may refer to the supermarket company Walmart
as Wal-Mart, whereas the other file refers to them
as Walmart, all one word.
When you get tabular data from sensors
there are additional challenges.
They may be missing fields.
For example, a given sensor might not
produce all of the different types of data.
So some sensors may produce temperature and humidity,
while other sensors provide temperature, humidity,
and light.
A sensor may be damaged, either permanently or intermittently.
And timestamps may be inaccurate or incorrect
between different sensors.
Other metadata for the sensors may also have errors.
For example, the location of a sensor or its identification
code.
And sensors may periodically go offline for a while,
leading to gaps in the data.