Some structured log files are created by print statements
in server processes.
And these include processes like web servers, database servers,
network file servers, and components
of the operating system.
All of these generate the semi-structured log files
that consist of human-readable text format files.
And this is a little ironic because it's
very rare for a human to actually read one of these log
files, and so oftentimes they're stored or archived in binary
or compressed format.
Now the format is either published in the specification
or defined by the code.
And as a result this can make it very
difficult to parse a semi-structured log
file, because the format can change at any time
and any time the code is changed or any time
the specification is changed.
So remember we looked at earlier in this course the Apache web
server log.
And you can see that each line here
consists of a request that's being made from a client
to the server.
Let's go through this file is defined by the Apache
common log format.
It specifies the long format file.
And here's an example line from that file.
The first component is the client IP address.
The second and the third components
are user identity from the remote machine,
and a hyphen means that that is not available.
The next component is the user identity from a local log on,
and a hyphen means that's not available.
The next component is the request time,
and this is broken up into a date, a time, and a times zone.
The next component is a client request,
and this consists of the request method, so get, post, put,
and so on.
The endpoint is a uniform resource identifier
which specifies what content the client is
trying to retrieve, and then finally the client protocol
version.
The last two components are status code at the server
sends back to the client and 200 means that everything went OK.
But there are other status codes like the 300 series, the 400
series and the 500 series.
The last component is the size of the object that's
returned to the client, and this is a hyphen
if no content is returned or sometimes a zero.
I have that underlined and bolded because this
is one of the things that makes parsing this kind of data
difficult, because sometimes it'll be a hyphen,
sometimes it'll be a zero.
You never know which one to expect.
You have to expect both.