In one of the labs for this course
you'll be exploring a web server access log from NASA,
the space agency in America.
This log covers 21 days and includes
over a million requests.
We've partially cleaned the log for you
to help you by removing some of the very hard to parse
requests.
Now, with a log like this there are many different questions
that you could ask.
For example, what are the statistics
for the content that's being returned,
the sizes, or the statuses?
What types of return codes occur?
How many 404-- that's page not found errors-- are there?
Those are important because that indicates
that someone wasn't able to find something
that they were looking for.
But you can also ask a lot of temporal questions,
like how many unique hosts were there per day?
Or how many requests were there per day?
Or on average, how many requests were there per host?
Or how many 404 errors were there on a daily basis?