So what's hard about cluster computing?
One challenge is how do we split work across machines?
Let's look at an example.
How do we count the number of occurrences
of each word in a document?
So here we have the document, I am Sam.
I am Sam.
Sam, I am.
Do you like green eggs and ham?
We'd like to count the words.
So, for example, there are three occurrences of I,
three occurrences of am, three occurrences of Sam,
and one of do, and one of you, and one of like, and so on.
So one approach we could do is to use a hash table.
So here we start with an empty hash table,
and we look at each word.
So we start with I. I doesn't appear in the hash table,
so we add it with a single occurrence.
We then examine the word am.
Am does not occur in the hash table,
so we add it with one occurrence.
We look at Sam.
Sam occurs not at all in our hash table,
so we add Sam to our hash table with one occurrence.
Now we see I, that appears in our hash table already,
and so we update the value to two.
And we can keep doing this for each
of the words in our document.