We can use Map Reduce also for sorting.
So here, the Reduce step, we partition
across the different machines based
upon the number of occurrences.
This allows us to answer questions
such as what word is used most?
So for the first machine, we send
all of the words that occur two or fewer times.
To the second machine, we send all
of the words that occur more than two times,
but four or fewer times.
We send, to the third machine, all
of the words that occur more than four times,
but five or fewer times.
And to the fourth machine, we send
all of the words that occur more than five times.
Now, what makes cloud computing difficult?
Well, there are two challenges we have to deal with.
The first is how do we divide work across machines?
We have to consider our network, how it's organized,
how fast it is, or how slow it is.
And we have to consider where data is located, data locality.
Because moving data may be very expensive,
especially if we have a lot of data that has to be moved.
The second thing that makes cluster computing difficult
is dealing with failures.
If a server fails on average every three years,
with 10,000 nodes in our cluster we'll see 10 faults per day.
But an even more difficult problem to deal with
is stragglers.
Nodes that have not failed, but are just running very slowly.
Maybe they're about to fail or they have some other problem.
And that's causing them to perform very slowly.
That's much more common than failures from a node
completely failing.