Technology trends show that the cost of memory is dropping.
Here's a graph that shows the cost of memory
with, on the x-axis, the year, and on the y-axis, price.
And this is a log-linear plot.
And so you can see that memory is dropping exponentially
over time.
In 2010, it only cost one cent per megabyte.
Now what does this mean?
Cheaper memory means we can put a lot more memory
in each server.
So now, the hardware that we have for Big Data
is lots of hard drives, lots of CPUs, and lots of memory.
So this gives us an opportunity.
We can keep more data in memory instead of writing it out
to slow disks, and then having to read it
right back in from those slow disks.
So this opportunity led to the creation of a new distributed
execution engine, Apache Spark.
So we'd like to use memory instead of disk.
Remember that what happens when we have an iterative task
is we read in data from disk, process it, write it out
to disk, read it in for the next iteration,
process it, write it back to disk, and so on.
Similarly, when we're performing a query,
we read information from disk, perform that query job
to give a result, and then for the next query
that comes in, we read the data back in all over again
and present a result. And if we're operating interactively,
this is going to be very, very slow.
So instead, what we'd like to do is use memory, and use memory
for in-data sharing.
So here, when we read in from disk for iteration one,
when we're finished, we write it to memory.
And that way, iteration two can read from very fast memory
and write to very fast memory.
The same thing with our query.
We do a one time processing step to read our data
into distributed memory, and from there all the queries
run from memory.
This can be anywhere from 10 to 100 times faster
than using the network or the disk.
The abstraction that Apache Spark provides
is that of the Resilient Distributed Data sets or RDDs.
We write our programs in terms of operations on distributed
data sets, and these are partition collections
of objects that are spread across a cluster stored
either in memory or on disk.
We can manipulate and build RDDs using
a diverse set of parallel transformations,
including map, filter, and join, and actions, including count,
collect, and save.
And Spark automatically keeps track
of how we created the RDDs and will automatically rebuild them
if a machine fails or a job is running slowly.