In big data there are two different kinds
of statistics that are very important,
descriptive and inferential.
With descriptive statistics, an example is the median.
Descriptive statistics describes the data,
but we can't generalize beyond that.
In this lecture, we'll look at exploratory data analysis,
which is a form of descriptive statistics.
Inferential statistics, examples are the t-test-- enable
inferences about populations beyond our data.
These are techniques that we leverage from machine learning
and prediction.
Examples of the kinds of business questions
we might want to ask include things like simple descriptive
statistics.
For example, who are the most profitable customers?
Or hypothesis testing.
Is there a difference in value to the company
of these different customers?
Or segmentation and classification.
What are the common characteristics
of these customers?
And finally prediction.
Will this new customer become a profitable customer?
And if so, how profitable?
We can apply these techniques in different ways.
Often, the kinds of questions that we
ask when we ask business questions are very casual.
What would happen if I show this ad?
It's often easier to ask correlational questions
such as, what happened in the past when I showed this ad.
Now there are two different forms
of learning that are interesting for big data.
There is supervised learning which is classification
and regression, and there's unsupervised
learning which is clustering and dimension reduction.
Now oftentimes we use unsupervised learning
inside a larger supervised learning problem.
So for example, auto-encoders are used for image recognition
neural networks.
Now here's some examples of the different learning techniques
that we might try to apply.
They fall again into the categories
of supervised learning and unsupervised learning.