Exploratory data analysis is based
on insights that were developed at Bell Labs in the 1960s.
They are techniques for visualizing and summarizing
data.
For example, what can the data tell us?
Now this is in contrast to confirmatory data analysis
where we already know what we're looking for
and we simply want to look at the data
and understand whether or not it confirms what we expect to see.
Exploratory data analysis introduced
many basic techniques, including the five-number summary,
box plots, and stem and leaf diagrams amongst other things.
Five-number summary is a way of looking
at the data in terms of its statistics
and includes looking at the extremes, the minimum
and the maximum, the median and quartiles.
And it's a technique that's much more
robust to skewed and long-tailed distributions
and looking at just simple statistics instead.
This was summarized in a book that was published in 1977.
So let's look at an example of a data set.
And this data set is called Anscombe's Quartet
and was developed in 1973.
We have four different data sets.
Set A, set B, set C, and set D.
Now the properties of each set are identical.
In particular, the mean of x in all of the sets is 9.
The sample variance of x is 11 in all of the data sets.
The mean of y is 7.5.
And the sample variance of y is 4.122.
You can fit a line to all of these data
sets using linear regression.
And that line would be identical.
y equals 3 plus 0.5x.
But what happens if we actually plot the data sets?
Wow.
We see that they're actually quite different.
So the takeaway here is that it's very important
to look at data graphically before you actually analyze it.
And basic statistics properties will often
fail to capture real-world complexities.
Here's another example.
This is a picture that was produced by Facebook
by plotting the friendship relationships of individuals
that are part of Facebook.
And they did that using Geotag information.
This kind of data art is actually
really quite fascinating.
You can see the continents here.
You can see countries.
You can see cities.
Even though they did not actually
use a world map when they plotted this,
they merely plotted the Geotag information.
So this is an example of how visualizing the data sets
can yield much more insights than simply just trying
to look at the underlying numbers that
are contained in the data set.