Many statistical tools, for example mean,
variance, t-test, ANOVA, assume the data is normally
distributed.
But very often, this is not the case.
So it's important to examine the histogram for your data set.
On the left, we have a curve that
is a normal distribution curve.
In the middle, we have a histogram
representing a positive skew in the data set.
And on the right curve, we have an example of negative skew
in a data set.
Now, there are other distributions
that are important that you will likely encounter in your work
with big data.
These include Poisson distributions.
These are a distribution of the counts that
occur at a certain rate, for example,
the observed frequency of a given term in a corpus,
or the number of visits to a website in a fixed time
interval, or the number of website clicks in an hour.
Another example of an important distribution is exponential.
And this is the interval between two such events
that you might see in a Poisson distribution.
Zipf, Pareto, and Yule distributions
govern the frequencies of different terms
in a document or website visits.
And binomial or multinomial distributions
are a number of counts of events,
for example, the number of six dies that show up
when you toss them n times.
It's very important to understand
your data's distribution before you
apply any model to that data.