Joseph Rhine was a parapsychologist in the 1950s.
He performed the following experiment.
He had subjects guess whether 10 hidden cards were red or blue.
He found that about one person in 1,000
had extrasensory perception.
They could correctly guess the color of all 10 cards.
They called back these psychic subjects
and had them repeat the test.
They all failed.
He concluded that the act of telling psychics
that they have psychic abilities causes them to lose it.
So what was wrong with his conclusion?
While it is the case that correlation does not
imply causation, that's not the problem here.
The real problem is, think about how many combinations
there are red and blue cards of length 10.
There's 2 the 10th power, or 1,024 combinations.
So there's a 0.98 probability that at least one subject
in 1,000 will guess correctly, which
is exactly what he observed.
And if you bring that subject back,
it's extremely unlikely-- very low probability--
that they'd be able to repeat that same observation.