Spark provides mllib, which is a scalable, distributed machine
learning library.
It provides a scikit-learn like Machine Learning tool kit
and interoperates with NumPy.
It provides functionality, including
classification, regression, and many other useful methods.
In this course, in the lab, you'll
be working on a problem of collaborative filtering.
The goal here is predict user's movie ratings
based on past ratings of other movies.
So the way to think about this is we have a set of users.
Those are columns here.
And we have a set of movies, which are rows here
in this Ratings matrix.
We can model Ratings as a product of User and Movie
Feature matrices of size U by K for the User matrix and M
by K for the Movie Feature matrix, where in this case
K is the rank.
And we want to learn K factors for each user
and learn K factors for each movie.
Now, we can do this by using the Alternating Least Squares
method.
We start with random A and B vectors.
And then we optimize the user vectors--
those are the A vectors-- based on the movies.
And we optimize the movie vectors--
that's the B vector-- based on the users.
And we repeat this process until we reach convergence.
You'll explore this in the lab.
Now, if you're interested in learning more
about Spark and Machine Learning,
I encourage you to take the Scalable Machine Learning
course, which starts June 22, 2015.