Here's an example of an instance of a student's relation.
The schema is the one that we saw earlier,
which is we have a student ID, we have a name,
we have a login, an age, and a GPA.
And associated with each one of those columns is a type.
in the instance we see here, we have three rows.
So the cardinality of this instance is three.
We have five columns, so the degree is five.
And you'll notice that all of the rows, the tuples,
are distinct.
Now, relational databases have several advantages.
They provide a well defined structure,
they maintain indices, which allow
them to have very high performance,
and the guarantee the consistency of the data
is maintained by using transactions.
The disadvantages of databases are
that they have a limited rigid structure,
and that most of the disk space ends up being taken up
by large indices.
Transactions can also be very slow,
and they have very poor support for sparse data.
So you can see that many of the things that
are advantages in one respect, are also disadvantages
in another respect.
Now looking at this last item, poor support for sparse data,
in more detail, we find that sparse data
is very common today.
Oftentimes, we want to store data with thousands of columns,
but not all the rows will have values for all of the columns.
In a typical database, the tables
might have dozens of columns.
But tables are going to be very wasteful for sparse data,
because most of the entries are going to be empty.