The structured query language, or SQL,
is a language for relational databases.
It's supported in pi spark by data frames.
And some of functionality that's SQL provides
is the ability to create, modify, and delete relations,
to add, modify, and remove tuples,
and to specify queries to find tuples matching criteria.
Let's look at this last functionality item,
specifying queries to find tuples that
match a particular criteria.
Single table queries are very straightforward in SQL.
To find all 18-year-old students,
we can write a select star from students s,
where s.age equals 18.
If we just want to find the names and logins,
we would write instead, select s.name comma, select,
.login from students s, where s.age equals 18.