We can specify a join over two tables as follows.
We have the table Enrolled E and Students S.
And we perform the following query.
SELECT S.name and E.cid FROM Students S and Enrolled E WHERE
S.sid equals E.sid.
Now, the first that the system is going to do
is to combine the two tables, S and E. It's
going to do this by performing a Cartesian product of the two
tables.
It'll do this by taking all the rows from E
and combining them with all of the rows from S.
And we will end up with the following table.
The next step is to use the WHERE
clause to select matching rows.
So in this case, it's where S.sid equals E.sid.
And we can see that there are two rows.
The next step is to filter columns
using the SELECT clause.
And the SELECT clause, here, is S.name and E.cid.
So now, we are able to return the result, which
is two tuples-- Jones and History 105 and Smith
and Physics 203.