SQL allows you to explicitly state the type of JOIN
that you want to perform.
So in this case, we have stated that we
want to SELECT S.name and E.classid FROM Students S
INNER JOIN Enrolled E ON S.sid equals E.sid.
This is the same as what we saw earlier.
It will combine the two tables, the Cartesian product,
and then select those tuples where S.sid equals E.sid.
Now, all of these are equivalent JOIN notations.
But the explicit versions are preferred.
In the explicit case, we have the example that we just saw,
SELECT S.name and E.classid FROM Students S
INNER JOIN Enrolled E ON S.sid equals E.sid,
or we can actually drop the keyword INNER as the default
JOIN is an INNER JOIN.
Now what we saw in the earlier example
was implicit JOIN notation.
But this has since been deprecated,
and so you shouldn't use it anymore.
Instead, you should explicitly say either INNER JOIN
or JOINED.