SQL provides support for multiple types of joins.
The type of the join controls how unmatched keys are handled.
Here we have an inner join, and it's
between two tables, students S, and enrolled E.
We can see in the table S, that there's
an unmatched key, brown.
And we can see in the table E, that there's an unmatched
key for English 10.
When producing the result, an inner join
will not include any tuples for which there's not a matching
key in the other relation.
The second type that we want to look at is a left outer join.
With a left outer join, if a key appears in the left table,
in this case, students S, but not in the right table,
in this case, enrolled E, then the key
is included, but with the value null.
So in this case, brown appears in the result,
but with a class ID that's null.
The third and last case that we can look at
is a right outer join.
With a right outer join, if a key appears in the right table,
in this case, enrolled E, but not in the left table,
in this case, students S, then the key
is included, but with the value null.
So in this case, English 10 is included as the class ID,
but the name is null.