Similar to Map Reduce, Spark supports Key-Value pairs
for RDDs.
Each element of a pair RDD is a pair tuple.
So here's an example where we applied
SC parallelize operation to a list consisting of two pairs.
The first pair is 1, 2.
The second pair is 3, 4.
This creates a new RDD that consists of two elements.
The first element being the pair 1, 2.
The second element being the pair 3, 4.
Now some of the Key-Value transformations
that we could perform include the following.
Reduce by key, which takes an RDD
and returns a new distributed RDD of key-value pairs
where the values for each key are aggregated using the given
reduced function.
And that reduced function has to be of the type
takes two values and returns one value.
The second key-value transformation is sort by key.
This returns a new data set of key-value pairs
that's sorted by keys in ascending order.
And the third key-value transformation
that we're going to look at is group by key.
This returns a new data set consisting of key and iterable
valued pairs.
So let's look at some examples.
So the first example is a reduced by key example.
So we start by parallelizing a list consisting
of three tuples.
1, 2; 3, 4; and 3, 6.
We then call the reduced by key transformation with a lambda
function that will sum the two values.
This produces a new RDD consisting of two elements.
The first element is the tuple 1, 2.
The second element is the tuple 3, 10.
The 10 came from taking the two tuples-- 3, 4 and 3,
6-- and combining the values using
the lambda function, which summed them
up giving us the value 10.
The second example is a sort by key example.
Here we create an RDD by parallelizing three tuples.
1 and the character A, 2 and the character C,
and 1 and the character B.
Now when we invoke sort by key, what we end up with
is a new RDD that consists of the elements.
A tuple of 1 and A, a tuple of 1 and B, and a tuple of 2 and C.
The third key value transformation
that we'd like to look at is a group by key.
So using that same RDD from the last example-- the tuple 1, A;
2, C; and 1, B-- when we apply the group
by key transformation, what we end up with
is a new RDD that contains two elements.
The first element is the tuple 1 and an iterable of A and B.
And the second element is the key 2 and an iterable
of C. You have to be very careful when using group by key
as it can cause a large amount of data movement
across the network.
It also can create very large iterables at a worker.
Imagine you have an RDD where you have 1 million pairs that
have the key 1.
All of the values will have to fit in a single worker
if you use group by key.
So instead of a group by key, consider
using reduced by key or a different key value
transformation.