Spark automatically creates closures
for functions that run on RDDs at workers,
and for any global variables that are used by those workers.
Now one closure per worker is sent with every task,
and there's no communication between workers.
And any changes that you make to the global variables that
are at the workers are not sent to the driver
or to other workers.
Now consider the following use cases.
What if we have an iterative or a single job
as a large global variable?
So this would result in sending a large read-only look-up table
to the workers or sending a large feature
vector in a machine learning algorithms to the workers.
Or what if we want to count events that
occur during job execution?
So for example, how many input lines were blank
or how many input records were corrupt?
The problem we have is that these closures
are automatically created are sent or re-sent with every job.
So for an interview job with a large global variable
we'll be sending that large global variable
with every single job to every single worker.
It's also very inefficient to continually send
large amounts of data to each worker,
and closures are one way from the driver to the worker.
So how can we count events that occur at a worker
and communicate that back to the driver?
Well, to do this, pySpark provides shared variables
in two different types.
The first is broadcast variables.
These enable us to efficiently send large read-only values
to all of the workers.
They're saved at the workers for use
in on or more Spark operations.
It's like sending a large read-only look-up table
to all of the nodes.
The second shared variable type is accumulators.
And they allow us to aggregate values from workers
back to the driver.
Now only the driver can access the value
of the accumulator for the tasks the accumulators
are basically write-only.
And we can use this as an example
to count errors that are seen in an RDD across workers.