In this course, we're using the Python programming interface
to Spark called pySpark.
pySpark provides an easy-to-use programming abstraction
in parallel runtime.
The way to think about it is you just
simply say, here's an operation, run it on all of the data.
To make all this work, RDDs are the key concept.
A Spark program consists of two programs, a driver program
and a workers program.
The drivers program runs on the driver machine.
And the worker programs run on cluster nodes
or in local threads.
And then RDDs are distributed across the workers.
The first thing a program does is to create a SparkContext
object.
This tells Spark how and where to access a cluster.
pySpark shell and Databricks Cloud
automatically create the sc variable for you.
In iPython and other programs, you
have to use a constructor to create a new Spark context.
You then use the Spark context to create our RDDs.
As a reminder, in the labs, we create
the Spark context for you, so you
don't have to worry about it.
The master parameter for a Spark context
determines which type and size of cluster to use.
And there are two choices, local clusters and remote clusters.
For local, you can either choose to run Spark with just one
worker, no parallelism.
Or you can run it with K worker threads
where, ideally, you want to set K
to be the same as the number of cores
that you have in your machine.
To work with clusters, you can either
connect to a Spark cluster or to an Apache Mesos cluster.
In the labs, we set the master parameter for you,
so you don't have to worry about this parameter.