So let's look at some examples of creating an RDD.
Here, we create an RDD from a Python list.
So we start with the list data, and then we
use sc.paralyze to create an RDD.
Now, no computation actually occurs when we
run the sc.paralyze operation.
All that occurs is Spark records how
to create an RDD that has four partitions from our list.
Here we can look at what happens when we use sc.textfile
with an actual file instead.
So we can use a file that comes from HDFS, from a text file,
from Hypertable, Amazon S3 Apache Hbase, SequenceFiles,
or any other Hadoop input format or even
a directory or wild card.
Again, all that will happen is Spark
will record that we want to create
an RDD, in this case with four partitions,
from the file README.md.
Now what actually happens when we
do something like sc.textfile?
We tell Spark that we want to create an RDD that's
distributed in four partitions.
Each element of that RDD is going
to be aligned from the input file.
And again, lazy evaluation means that no execution
happens right now.
All that happens is Spark records
how to create the RDD from that text file.