-Let's look at the transformations
that we just talked about.
So here, we start with creating an RDD using sc.parallelize
of a list-- the list one, two, three, four.
Then we apply the transformation map.
And we pass in a lambda function that will double each element.
Now, spark turns this function literal into a closure
and passes it automatically to the worker.
So the code in black runs at the driver.
The code in green runs at individual workers.
So what will happen here is it'll take the RDD one, two,
three, four, and it'll transform it into two, four, six, eight.
Again, nothing actually happens until an action is performed.
But this is part of the recipe that we're constructing.
Now alternatively, we could have used a filter transformation.
Here, the lambda function will return true
if the element, modulo two, equals zero.
So this will take our RDD of one, two, three, four,
and return elements two, and four.
So we construct a new RDD consisting of two and four.
The last transformation on this slide
is the distinct transformation.
So we start by parallellizing the list one, four, two, two,
three.
And then, we take and pass that to the distinct transformation.
That would give us a new RDD that
only contains the distinct elements of the input RDD.
So this creates a new RDD with only one, four, two, and three.
Those are the unique elements of the input RDD.
Here's another example of a transformation, the map
transformation.
So we pass in an RDD that we created using sc.parallelize
with one, two, three.
And that is then passed to a map with a lambda function
that will return x and x plus five as each element.
So this takes-- as a list-- this takes that RDD that
was one, two, three, and creates a new RDD where
each element of the RDD is a list.
So we have, now, first element of the RDD is one and six.
Second element is two and seven.
And the third element is a list of three and eight.
Now let's compare this to what happens when we use flat map.
When we use flat map, we would create the same RDD .
But then it flattens that RDD and takes each list
and turns it into individual elements.
So instead, we end up with the RDD
consisting of the elements one, six, two, seve, three,
and eight.
So let's look at what happens when we transform a text
file based RDD.
So here, we create a new RDD lines from a text file.
And this is going to create an RDD with four partitions.
We then filter out lines that are comments.
And so here we're passing in a function
instead of passing in a lambda.
And the function here is called isComment.
And it doesn't matter what the function is actually doing,
but what we'll say is if the line is a comment,
we want it removed from the RDD.
So we'll create a new RDD comments
that contains only those elements from lines
that are not comments.
Now lazy evaluation means that nothing is actually
going to happen right now.
Spark, instead, will save a recipe for how it's
going to transform the source.