Spark actions cause Spark to execute the recipe
to transform the source through the mechanism for getting
results out of Spark.
Here are four Spark actions.
The first action is reduce.
Reduce aggregates a data set element using a function.
That function takes two arguments and returns one.
It has to be commutative and associative so that it can be
computed correctly in parallel.
The take action returns an array with the first n elements.
And the collect action returns all of the elements of the RDD
as an array, so you have to make sure that all of that data
will fit in the driver program.
Takeordered returns n elements ordered in ascending order
or as specified by the optional key function.
So let's look at some examples.
We start with parallelizing a list, one two three,
and then we use the reduce action.
We pass in a lambda function that will multiply the two
elements together.
So this will multiply all of the elements of the lists
together to produce a single value, the value 6.
1 times 2 times 3.
The take action will return the first two elements of the rdd.
So in this case it returns one and two
as a list at the driver.
Collect returns all of the elements of the rdd
So in this case that's one, two, three.
And again, always be careful when using
collect to make sure that the results will actually
fit in the driver's memory.
Here we apply the parallelize option
to the list five, three, one, two.
This returns an rdd containing five, three, one, and two.
We then use takeordered to take the first three elements.
We pass in a key function that will
multiply an element by minus 1.
So instead of takeordered returning the first three
elements in increasing value, it will
return the decreasing value.
And so we'll get back five, three, and two
as a list at the driver.