Let's look at the example that we created before.
So here, we have the creation of an RDD lines
from a text file with four partitions.
Nothing happens when we actually do that until we
execute an action.
The action we're going to execute in this case
is the count function, which returns
a count of the number of elements in an RDD.
So when we run the command, print
lines.count, that will cause Spark
to read the data from the text file,
to sum the number of lines per partition,
and then to combine those sums in the driver.
And we'll find out how many lines are in our program.
Now if we add another transformation,
in this case, a filter transformation,
that's going to create an RDD that contains
the lines that are comments.
And then we want to see how many comments lines there are.
We can do comments.count.
This is going to cause Spark to re-compute lines.
It will re-read all of the data from that text file
again, sum within the partition the number
of lines, so the number of elements,
and then combine those sums in the driver.