The "R" language is an evolution of the "S" language
that was developed at Bell Labs for exploratory data analysis.
The idea is to allow interactive exploration and visualization
of data.
And it's the preferred language for statisticians
and used by many data scientists.
Its features include being the most comprehensive collection
of statistical models and distributions,
and also CRAN, which is a very large repository of open source
statistical models.
Now, let's talk about some definitions.
The mean of a set of values is the average of the values,
and the variance is a measure of the width of a distribution.
The standard deviation is the square root of the variance,
and a normal distribution is characterized
by a mean and a variance.
Here we have a figure that shows an example
of a normal distribution.
In probability theory, the central limit theorem
states that the distribution of a sum
or mean of n independent identically
distributed random variables approaches
a normal distribution as the number of variables
approaches infinity.
The common parametric statistical test,
for example t-test and ANOVA, assume
that you have a normally distributed data set.
But they also depend on the sample mean and variance.
These types of tests work reasonably
well for data that are not normally distributed,
as long as the samples are not too small.