Data quality constraints are a way of capturing many data
quality problems.
For example, we can use the schema
static constraints-- say, for example, nulls are not allowed,
or specifying the field domains, or specifying constraints
on foreign keys.
But many other data quality problems
are due to problems in the workflow.
These, we can capture with dynamic constraints--
for example, saying that all orders above $200
are processed by biller number 2.
But data quality constraints often
follow an 80-20 rule, where a few constraints capture
most cases, but we need thousands of constraints
to capture the last few cases.
Constraints are measurable.
So maybe this is a way of getting towards data quality
metrics.
In terms of data quality metrics,
we want a measurable quantity-- something
that indicates what is wrong and how we can improve.
Now, the challenge here is that we
have to realize that data quality is a messy problem.
And there's no set of numbers that's going to be perfect.
But we want metrics that are directionally correct,
and improve as we use our data.
Examples of types of metrics are static and dynamic constraints,
or operational and diagnostic metrics.
Now, there's a very large number of possible metrics
that we could have.
We want to choose the most important ones.
So examples of data quality metrics that we could consider
are conformance to schema.
We can evaluate our constraints on a snapshot of our database.
Or, conformance to business rules.
We can evaluate our constraints every time
the database changes.
Accuracy.
We can either performer a very expensive inventory,
or, alternatively, we could track complaints.
That's sort of a proxy metric.
Another alternative is to periodically audit our data set
and see if the samples match what
we expect in terms of accuracy.
There are other data quality metric issues,
like accessibility or interpretability.
We can also have glitches in our analysis that we want to track.
Or we could have metrics around successful completion
of the end-to-end process.