We begin with data gathering.
How does the data actually enter the system?
This is part of the experimentation or observation
or collection process.
It can be a source of problems, including
issues around manual entry of information
versus automated data entry.
It can be due to approximations or surrogates,
maybe constraints in the software
or constraints in the hardware.
It can be due to a lack of uniform standards
for content and formats.
It can be due to parallel data entry.
This causes duplicates.
Or it can be due to measurement or sensor errors.
Some potential solutions to the data gathering problem
are to be preemptive.
Design a good process architecture that
builds in integrity checks.
Design good process management that rewards accurate
data entry, sharing and stewards.
These are the people who are responsible for data entry.
Also, consider being retrospective.
The cleaning focus should focus on things
like duplicate removal, or merging and purging
bad information, or performing tasks like name and address
matching, or field value standardization.
Also, think about a diagnostic focus--
automating the detection of problems
during the data gathering phase.