In this segment, we'll talk about how we can
use probabilistic predictions.
We'll first talk about how we can incorporate domain
knowledge when thresholding our probabilities to generate
class predictions.
We'll then talk about how we might want to work directly
with probabilistic predictions and how in such cases,
logistic loss is an appropriate evaluation metric.
In the previous segment, we discussed
how we can convert probabilistic predictions
to class predictions by thresholding them.
If we look at our rain example, and if we
assume a threshold of 0.5, then a conditional probability
prediction of 0.05 would lead to a class prediction of y hat
equals 0.
And a conditional probability prediction of 0.9
would lead to a class prediction of y hat equals 1.
We also showed that in the context of logistic regression,
using a threshold value of 0.5 led to the same decision
boundary as simply looking at the sine of w transpose x,
or of a dot product between our model and our features.
But when we have access to fine-grained probabilistic
predictions, we don't necessarily
have to set our threshold to 0.5.
Let's consider a spam detection example to see this point.
And suppose that we have a trained model that
gives us conditional probabilities
that an email will be spam.
Now, imagine that we've made an incorrect spam prediction.
We can potentially make two types of mistakes.
The first type, which we call a false positive,
occurs when we classify a legitimate email as spam.
The second type, which we call a false negative,
occurs when we classify a spam email as a legitimate one.
In this application, it's reasonable to argue
that false positives are more harmful than false negatives.
In other words, users will likely
be more frustrated if an email from a close friend
gets lost in a spam filter than if a spam
email doesn't get filtered and shows up in their inbox.
These two types of errors are typically
at odds with each other.
Or, in other words, we often trade off one type of error
for the other.
In our spam application, we might
be willing to accept a few more false negatives in exchange
for reducing the number of false positives.
When working with probabilistic predictions,
we can make these trade-offs by adjusting our threshold.
Using a higher threshold leads to a classifier
that is more conservative in identifying an email as spam.
Assuming we want to change our threshold,
how can we determine the best choice?
One natural way to do this is to use a ROC plot, which
visualizes the trade-offs we make
as we change our threshold.
In particular, a ROC plot focuses on two standard metrics
that are often at odds with one another, namely
the false positive rate, or FPR, and the true positive rate,
or TPR.
Using our spam detection application
as a running example, we can interpret
FPR as the percentage of legitimate emails
that are incorrectly predicted as spam.
And we can view TPR as the percentage of spam emails
that are correctly predicted as spam.
In an ideal world, we would have an FPR of 0 and a TPR of 1.
An FPR of 0 would mean that none of our legitimate emails
were incorrectly classified as spam.
And a TPR of 1 would mean that all spam emails were correctly
classified as spam.
Therefore, having both an FPR of 0 and a TPR of 1
would imply a perfect classifier.
In a ROC plot, this corresponds to being
on the top left of the plot.
As a second baseline, imagine that we flipped a fair coin
to generate each of our predictions, in which
case, on average, half of our emails
would be classified as spam, and half would be non-spam.
In this case, both the FPR and the TPR would equal 0.5 More
generally, we could flip a biased coin,
or, in other words, a coin that lands on
heads with some probability P. And in this case,
the dotted line in the ROC plot visualizes
the results of making these random predictions,
with each point on this dotted line corresponding
to a different value of p.
Now that we've established these baselines,
let's see how we can use a ROC plot to evaluate a classifier.
Imagine that we've trained a classifier that
returns probabilistic predictions, as in the case
of logistic regression.
Let's also assume that we're using a validation set
to find a good threshold.
Then we can use our classifier to generate
conditional probabilities for observations in our validation
set.
And once we have these probabilities,
we can generate a ROC plot by varying
the threshold we use to convert these probabilities to class
predictions, and computing FPR and TPR
at each of these thresholds.
Our threshold can range from 0 to 1,
and each point on the ROC plot corresponds
to a distinct threshold.
For instance, in one extreme, where our threshold equals 0,
we interpret all positive probability predictions
as being spam.
Or, in other words, we aggressively
predict everything to be spam.
By doing so, our TPR equals 1, which is good.
But our FPR is also equal to 1, which is bad.
In the other extreme, we can set our threshold
to equal 1, in which case we never classify anything
as spam.
In this conservative setting, we never have any false positives,
and thus our FPR is 0, which is a good thing.
But now our TPR is also 0, which is a bad thing.
And in practice, we trade off TPR and FPR
in an application-specific way.
For instance, in our spam application,
since we're particularly concerned about classifying
a legitimate email as spam, we might
be willing to tolerate at most a 10% false positive rate.
And with this constraint in mind,
we can then pick the threshold that maximizes the TPR, given
that FPR can be at most 10%.
We've seen that ROC plots are a powerful tool for choosing
the most appropriate threshold when we ultimately
need to make class predictions.
However, in some cases, we might not
want to make class predictions at all.
Instead, we might want to work directly with probabilities
as they provide more granular information.
For instance, let's go back to our clickthrough rate
prediction example.
As we know, click events are rare.
And as a result, our predicted click probabilities
will be uniformly low.
So unless we picked some very low threshold,
the vast majority of our class predictions
will all be y hat equals 0.
However, in this application, we're
not interested in the class prediction, but rather
the probabilities themselves.
We want to know which events are most likely to occur
and how much more likely certain events are relative to others.
We may also want to combine these predictions
with other information and thus don't want a threshold,
as we'll lose this fine-grained information by doing so.
In such cases, it makes sense to work directly
with the probabilities and to evaluate our predictive models
based on the quality of these probabilities
rather than on their class predictions.
In these cases, it makes sense to use
the logistic loss for evaluation rather than the 0-1 loss.
Let's take a look at the logistic loss
to better understand why this is the case.
Note that we initially introduced logistic loss
when assuming that the labels were either
equal to negative 1 or 1.
Here, however, we're using our new notation,
where the labels are either 0 or 1, which
makes the logistic loss easier to interpret.
With our new notation, the logistic loss
takes in two values as parameters.
The first parameter is the probabilistic prediction,
which is a number ranging from 0 to 1.
And the second is the true label,
which is a discrete value that either equals 0 or 1.
We can define the logistic loss with different expressions
depending on the value of y.
First, let's consider the case when y equals 1.
In this case, we want the predicted probability
to be as close to 1 as possible.
The blue line shows the behavior of a logistic loss
in this setting.
And, as we can see, we incur no loss or penalty
when the probability equals 1, and we
incur an increasingly large penalty as the probability
moves away from 1.
We see an analogous situation when y equals 0,
where the loss equals 0 if the predicted probability equals 0,
and we suffer an increasing penalty or loss
as the probability increases.
So in comparison to the 0-1 loss, which either returns
a penalty of 0 or 1, the log loss
is a more fine-grained metric for evaluating the accuracy
of probabilistic predictions.