In this segment, we'll talk about how
we can deal with categorical data when training a model.
In particular, we'll introduce one-hot encoding,
which is a standard technique for converting
categorical features into numerical ones.
Recall the optimization problem we
solved for logistic regression.
And notice that the data points appear in the optimization
in the form of dot products.
And thus, when training a logistic regression model,
we assume that the features are numerical.
In fact, many learning models assume
that all features used to represent an observation
are numeric.
In practice, our raw data is sometimes numeric.
And examples include images being
represented via pixels or user ratings represented
as integer scores.
But in many other cases, the raw data
is not numeric, which can be problematic,
given the assumptions of many learning methods.
For instance, data is often represented via text,
as is the case with web hypertext,
emails, or genomic sequencing data.
As another example, let's consider the problem
of clickthrough rate prediction.
As we've previously discussed, in this problem
we work with features describing a user, an advertiser,
and a publisher, and many relevant features
will be non-numeric.
So for instance, non-numeric features
such as gender, nationality, and occupation
could be relevant for a user.
Descriptive non-numeric features for both advertisers
and publishers include their industry and their location.
And finally, we want to include features
specific to the particular ad and publisher
site under consideration, and the text and the language
of the ad and the publisher site are both useful features,
as is the target demographic for both the ad and the site.
So what do we do when our data is non-numeric,
as it so often is the case?
The first option is to simply restrict ourselves
to methods that natively support non-numeric features.
And it is the case that some useful learning methods,
in particular, decision trees and ensembles of trees,
naturally support non-numeric features.
However, this approach severely limits our options.
A second approach is to convert non-numeric features
to numeric ones, which allows us a wide range of learning
methods to choose from.
The question, of course, though, is how we can effectively
perform this conversion.
Before answering this question, let's
talk about the two main types of non-numeric features
that we encounter.
First, we have categorical features.
These are features that contain two or more categories,
and these categories have no intrinsic ordering.
So, for example, consider a country feature
with three categories, Argentina, USA, and France.
Although people may have a lot of national pride,
there's no underlying ordering or ranking
of these three categories.
And hence, the country feature is an example
of a categorical feature.
Other examples of categorical features
include gender, occupation, and language.
The second common class of non-numeric features
are ordinal features.
Ordinal features, again, have two or more categories.
But here, these categories do contain
some ranking information but only
relative ordering information.
And these types of features often
arise in survey questions.
For instance, consider a survey question
that asks someone to rate their health
as poor, reasonable, good, or excellent.
From this question, we could define a health feature
with four categories.
And these four categories can be ranked,
with excellent being the best and poor being the worst.
However, there's not necessarily a consistent spacing
between these categories.
Thus the help feature is an example of an ordinal feature.
Now that we have a basic understanding
of the main types of non-numeric features,
let's consider one seemingly reasonable strategy
for converting non-numeric features to numeric ones.
Specifically, we could represent a non-numeric feature
with a single numeric feature by representing each category
with a distinct number.
So let's look at an example of how the strategy might work.
And to do that, we'll go back to our health feature, where
we have four health categories ranging from poor to excellent.
According to this strategy, we would
assign each of the four categories
to integer values ranging from 1 to 4.
At first glance, this seems like a reasonable strategy,
and, in fact, using a single numerical feature
does preserve the ordering for ordinal features.
However, doing this introduces a notion
of closeness between the ordinal categories that
didn't previously exist.
So, for instance, since the "good" category is represented
by 3, and the "poor" category is represented by 1,
this numerical representation implies
that the distance between good and poor equals 2, 3 minus 1.
Similarly, the distance between excellent and poor
is 3, or 4 minus 1.
This type of distance information
didn't exist in our initial representation
of health categories.
This becomes an even bigger issue
when applying this strategy on categorical features.
So let's go back to our country feature example,
where our three categories are Argentina, France, and USA.
According to the proposed strategy,
we would assign integer values to each category,
for instance, defining Argentina as 1, France as 2,
and USA as 3.
But this mapping introduces relationships
between these categories that don't otherwise exist.
Our particular choice implies that France
is in between the other two countries,
even though the original categories have
no intrinsic ordering.
So as we've seen, using a single numeric feature
is not such a good idea, as it introduces
spurious relationships between the categories.
To get around this issue, we can use a different strategy
called one-hot encoding.
In this strategy, we create a separate dummy variable
for each category.
Going back to the country feature example,
since we have three categories, the one-hot encoding strategy
would create three new binary dummy features.
For instance, the first feature could correspond to Argentina,
the second feature could correspond to France,
and the third one to USA.
If the original categorical feature is Argentina,
we'd set the first binary feature to 1 and the other two
binary features to 0.
And more generally, we set exactly one of these binary
features equal to 1, depending on the value of the underlying
categorical feature.
By creating separate features for each category,
we don't introduce any spurious relationships,
and this strategy works well both for categorical and
ordinal features.