In this segment, we'll go through an example of how
to compute one-hot encoded, or OHE features,
and we'll then discuss how to efficiently store
these OHE features.
Consider a categorical animal data set
comprised of three features.
The first is the type of animal, and the categories here
are bear, cat, and mouse.
The second is the animal's color,
and the categories are black and tabby.
The third feature is the animal's diet,
and the categories are mouse and salmon.
Note that this third feature is optional,
meaning that some observations won't have
any value for this feature.
And also note that the category "mouse"
appears in two features, in particular, the animal
and the diet feature.
Now let's look at the data set itself,
which is three observations.
The first observation, A1, is a black mouse
that has no value for the diet feature,
as indicated by the dash.
The second observation is a tabby cat
whose diet consists of mice.
The third feature is a black bear that eats salmon.
So our question is how can we compute OHE features
from the data set.
Creating OHE features is a two-step process
where the first step involves creating an OHE dictionary.
In particular, recall that we have
three categorical features, with the first feature having three
categories, and the second two features each having
two categories.
So in total, there are seven distinct categories
across these three features.
And thus we need seven binary dummy variables
to represent them using a one-hot encoding.
And note that the mouse category is
distinct for the animal and the diet features.
So our first goal is to create a dictionary that
maps each category to a dummy feature.
We have seven categories and seven dummy variables,
and we want to create a one-to-one mapping.
We describe each category is a tuple containing the feature
name and the categorical value.
So a tuple, animal, bear, is one such category,
and we can map it to the dummy variable 0.
Similarly, we can map the tuple animal, cat
to the dummy variable 1.
And we can perform a similar process
for all of the other categories.
And note that by defining each category
as a tuple, the tuples animal, mouse and diet,
mouse are treated distinctly, which
is what we want to be doing.
Now we have our OHE dictionary, we can create OHE features.
To do this, we simply map each non-numeric feature
to its binary dummy feature.
So for instance, the numeric representation of A1
is 0, 0, 1, 1, 0, 0, 0.
Let's see how we arrive at this representation.
We see that A1's animal feature equals mouse.
And in our OHE dictionary, this corresponds
to the tuple animal, mouse.
And our dictionary tells us that this tuple corresponds
to the dummy feature 2.
As a result, we can set the second feature equal to 1.
And note that we're cutting starting from 0
or using a zero-based numbering system.
Similarly, A1's color feature is black.
So again, we look up in our OHE dictionary,
and we see that this corresponds to dummy feature 3.
So as before, we can now set the corresponding dummy feature,
in this case feature 3, equal to 1.
Now that we've walked through an example of how
to create OHE features, let's talk
about how we can store them.
Note that for a given categorical feature, at most
a single OHE dummy feature is non-zero.
In other words, most of our OHE features are equal to 0,
or our OHE features are sparse.
When storing OHE features, we can take
advantage of this sparsity.
The standard way to represent features
is via a dense representation, where we store all numbers
regardless of their value.
So for instance, in this example,
we would store each of the seven values
in A1's feature representation as a double.
However, an alternative way to store our features
is to store the indices and values for all non-zero entries
and assume that all other entries equal 0.
So back to our A1 example, this would
mean that we would store two tuples or a total of four
values.
In each of these tuples, the first component
is the feature index, and the second component
is the value of this feature.
When our data is sparse, using a sparse representation
can lead to a dramatic savings, both in terms
of storage and computation.
So let's consider an example of storing
a data set with 10 million observations and 1,000
features.
And let's assume that on average, 1% of the features
are equal to 0.
In our standard dense representation,
we would store each number in this matrix using
a single double, and this leads to a total
of 80 gigabytes of storage.
In contrast, using a sparse representation,
we could represent each non-zero entry via two doubles, one
to store the value and the other to store the index
or location of this feature.
In our example, this would lead to a 50x savings in storage.
This more compact representation would also directly translate
into computational savings when performing
matrix operations, such as multiplies or inversions.