In this segment, we'll discuss how OHE features can
be high dimensional, which can lead both
to statistical and computational challenges.
We'll then introduce the technique
of feature hashing, which can be used
to reduce the dimensionality of OHE features.
In previous segments, we discussed the technique
of One-Hot-Encoding, to convert categorical features
into numeric ones.
This technique creates a dummy feature for each category,
and by doing so we avoid introducing
spurious relationships in our numeric representation.
However, a consequence of OHE features
is that they drastically increase the dimensionality
of our data, as the number of features in an OHE
representation equals the total number of categories
in our data.
This is a major issue in the context of clickthrough rate
prediction, as our initial user, ad,
and publisher features include many names and a lot of text.
OHE features can be problematic whenever
we're working with text data.
For instance, as we discussed earlier in the course,
we often use a bag of words representation
to represent documents with a vocabulary of words.
There are over one million words in the English language alone,
and thus the size of our vocabulary
can be quite large, resulting in high dimensional
representation.
Additionally, we sometimes would like
to create a richer representation of our text data
by considering all pairs of adjacent words,
using a so-called bigram representation.
This bigram representation is similar in spirit
to the idea of quadratic features discussed earlier
in the course.
Bigram representations of text documents
result in even larger feature dimensionality.
High dimensionality features can cause
problems, both statistically and computational.
Statistically, we typically need more observations
when we are learning with more features.
And even though we usually have many observations
in large scale settings, it is still harder
to learn models with more features.
Computationally, larger feature vectors
require increased storage and computation,
with communication in particular being the bottleneck.
For instance, when training linear models
we're learning d dimensional parameter vectors.
And when training with gradient descent,
we need to communicate the current parameter
factor after each iteration.
For large d, this can become an expensive process.
Given these issues, it would be nice
if we could reduce the dimension of our OHE features.
The first idea that we might have
is to simply discard rare features.
For instance, in a bag of word representation,
we could remove words that appear very infrequently
throughout our training set.
However, infrequent features are not necessarily uninformative,
and this approach might lead us to throw out
useful information.
Additionally, even if we discard rare features,
we still must first compute the full OHE features,
and creating the OHE dictionary can be particularly expensive.
Feature hashing provides an alternative method
for reducing the dimension of OHE features.
By using hashing principles, we can
create a lower dimensional feature representation
and completely skip the process of creating an OHE dictionary.
Feature hashing preserves the sparsity of OHE features,
and is motivated by theoretical arguments.
It's also worth noting that the feature hashing can
be interpreted as an unsupervised learning
method, which is performed as a pre-processing step
for a downstream supervised learning task.
Now, let's talk more about feature hashing.
Hashing is a rich area of computer science,
with hash tables being an important data
structure for data lookup, and with hash functions having
applications in cryptography.
We won't discuss these details here,
but we'll simply note that hash tables have a fixed
number of buckets, and that hash functions map an object to one
of these m buckets.
In particular, hash functions are
designed to efficiently compute this mapping
and to distribute objects fairly evenly across buckets.
In the context of feature hashing,
each feature category is an object,
and we have fewer buckets than feature categories.
So in contrast to the OHE dictionary,
which is a one to one mapping between feature categories
and dummy features, feature hashing uses a many to one
mapping between feature categories and buckets.
In other words, different categories
are bound to collide or map to the same bucket.
These bucket indices are what we define as our hashed features.
So now let's consider a concrete example
to understand how feature hashing works.
We'll use the same categorical animal data
set that we did earlier, which involves
three categories, animal, color, and diet,
in seven total feature categories.
Suppose the number of buckets equals m equals 4,
and that we've already selected a hash function to map future
categories to buckets.
If we consider the first data point,
A1, we see that the hash function
maps the two-pole animal, comma, mouse, to bucket three,
and it maps the two-poll pull color, black, to bucket two.
Since we have four buckets total,
this leads to a feature vector of length 4 for A1,
with the second and third hashed features equal to one.
We can do something similar with the second data point, A2,
and we see that the two poles, animal, comma, cat,
and color, comma, tabby, both map to bucket 0.
This is an example of a hash collision.
The mapping of the two-pole diet, comma, mouse,
shows yet another example of a collision,
as the two-pole color, comma, black previously
mapped to bucket two, as well.
Overall, this means that we represent
A2 with the following four dimensional vector.
Note here that we have a value of 2 in Feature 0,
which is due to the fact that two of the categorical
features for A2 both map to bucket 0.
We also see a value of 1 in feature two.
We can go through the same exercise for the third data
point, A3, to obtain its hash feature representation.
As we saw in this toy example, when we have more feature
categories than we have buckets, we're bound to have collisions.
And thus, arbitrary feature categories
will be grouped together.
It turns out that in spite of the slightly strange behavior,
feature hashing has nice theoretical properties.
In particular, many learning methods
can be interpreted as relying on training data
only in terms of pairwise inner products between the data
points.
In the context of OHE features, if we're
going to approximate these OHE features with a more
compact feature representation, then we
want this compact feature representation
to do a good job of approximating inner products
computed on OHE features.
And it turns out that under certain conditions,
hashed features lead to good approximations
of these inner products, theoretically.
Moreover, hashed features have been used in practice
and have resulted in good practical performance
on various text classification tasks.
And so in summary, hash features are a reasonable alternative
to OHE features.
Hash features can also be computed
in a fairly straightforward fashion in a distributed
setting.
Once we've decided on a hash function,
we first need to apply this function to the raw data.
This is a local computation requiring no communication,
and hash functions are generally fast and computable.
As shown in the Spark code snippet,
this step can be written by a single map expression.
In the second step, we can store hashed features
in a sparse representation, in order to save storage space
and reduce the computational burden in subsequent steps
of our pipeline.
This step can also be expressed as a single map operation.