The goals of this course include learning about data science,
where does Big Data come from, performing observation
and experimentation, and the elements of data science, which
include data acquisition, data preparation, analysis,
data presentation, and data products.
Another goal of the course is that you
learn how to perform data science,
that you understand data quality and how to clean and manipulate
data sets, how to use and parse data representations,
and how to use basic machine learning
algorithms and libraries.
And that you learn how to write big data applications
and perform exploratory data analysis.
The third goal of this course is that you learn
to write Apache Spark programs.
You'll learn about the history and development of Apache
Spark, along with its conceptual model,
how the Spark cluster model works.
And you'll learn about Spark essentials, transformations,
actions, persistence, broadcast variables, accumulators,
key value pairs, and the Python spark API, pySpark.
You'll also learn how to debug Spark programs
and how to use Spark's mllib library for machine learning.