This is a brief history of data analysis.
In the 1930s, Fisher proposed a design
of experiments along with his statistical tests ANOVA,
and Fisher's exact tests.
He's also credited with the quotation,
"Correlation does not imply causation."
This is ironic given that Fisher was a lifelong pipe smoker,
and derided studies that showed any link between smoking
and cancer.
In the later 1930s, Demming proposed
the idea of quality control using statistical sampling.
Luhn, in the '50s, proposed the idea
of using indexing and information retrieval
methods with text data for the purposes of business
intelligence.
And Tukey, in 1977, wrote the book, Exploratory Data
Analysis.
This led to the development of the S and S+ languages,
along with a language you've perhaps heard of, R.
Dresner is a modern business intelligence proponent.
And in 1997, Mitchell wrote the Machine Learning book that
is still a bestseller today.
In 1996, two Stanford Ph.D. Graduate students
wrote a prototype search engine which ultimately led to Google.
And Microsoft, in 2007, released a data-driven science ebook
titled The Fourth Paradigm.
Norvig proposed the unreasonable effectiveness of data.
The idea that multiple small models and lots of data
is much more effective than building very complex models.
And The Economist in 2010 published
an issue titled "The Data Deluge," ground
the exponential growth in data volume.