Let's look at some of the sources of big data.
Much of what we do occurs online,
and potentially we could record every click, so every website
that you click on, every ad you view, every billing event,
every fast-forward or pause while you're watching a video,
like for example this course video.
Every request that's made from a client
to a server, every transaction, every network
message, and every fault.
Anything that occurs online potentially could be recorded.
And in fact a lot of it is recorded, but very little of it
actually gets analyzed, and that's
why I have a picture of an iceberg on this slide,
because a phenomenal amount of data is collected
but only a tiny amount of that data is analyzed.
Another source of big data is the users.
User-generated content.
And this is a big source on the web and an even larger growing
source from mobile devices.
So every post that you make on Facebook or every picture
you send on Instagram or every review
that you write for Yelp or TripAdvisor or every tweet
you send on Twitter or video that you post to YouTube.
Now individually this user-generated content
is not very large, but taken across the billions
of internet users, it's a massive amount of data.
Another source of big data is health
and scientific computing.
So here on the left we have a graph
showing various repositories-- Wikipedia,
the Library of Congress, tweets per year,
and the Large Hadron Collider.
It generates more data in a year than all the other data
sources combined.
In the middle we have genome sequencing data.
Sequencing data, the cost of performing sequencing,
is dropping exponentially, much faster than Moore's Law,
so as result we're collecting more sequencing data than ever
before.
And so you see the graph in the middle
shows exponential growth in the amount of sequencing data
that we have.
Graphs are also an interesting source of big data.
These graphs include things like social networks,
telecommunication networks, computer networks,
road networks, and collaborations
or relationships.
And some of these graphs can be absolutely enormous.
Think about Facebook's user graph.
In fact, later on in this course we'll
look at a picture of the user graph.
Another source of big data is log files.
These are files that are generated
by servers around the internet.
So here's an example of an Apache web server log,
and it records every click.
So every time your web browser makes a request
to a web server, that gets recorded in the log file.
And later on in this class we're actually
going to look at a log file and you're
going to perform some analysis on it using Spark.
Here's an example of a machine log file,
and there are hundreds of millions of machines out there.
Each machine is generating a log file
like this of the applications that run
or any errors that occur in those applications
or in the operating system or in the operating system processes.
All that gets recorded.
But an even bigger source of data
potentially is the internet of things.
Here's an example of an internet of things device.
And typically an internet of things device
has a processor, a little bit of memory,
and communications capability.
It also some sensors and sometimes and actuators.
So here at Berkeley, one of the research projects
built the internet of things device
you see in the upper right, which
is a little sensor mode that measures
humidity and temperature.
And they put those into the Redwood forests
we have here in California at different heights in a Redwood
tree.
Now taken individually, each sensor
generates a very small amount of data,
but imagine the amount of data they
gets generated from an entire forest full of these sensors.
Here's another example of an internet of things
device, an RFID tag.
This is a California FasTrak Electronic Toll Collection
transponder.
We use it here in California to pay our tolls on the highways.
But it's also used to collect data that's
used for traffic reporting, because they
put sensors that measure these transponders
all over the highways.
Now what we do all we have big data?
So let's say we have crowd sourcing.
We have lots of users that are collaborating to provide data.
We combine that with a physical terrain model and sensors
which could either be road highway sensors that
are embedded in the roadway or they
could be individual users' phones
running mapping applications.
We then assimilate together all of that data
and we can produce a picture like the one
you see here at the bottom.
This is a map of the city of Berkeley showing
the traffic in the city and what's
interesting is in without seeing the underlying physical model
you could see what the major arteries and traffic ways are
in our city.