Let's talk about the differences between Spark and Map Reduce.
In Map Reduce, your only option for storage is the disk.
In Spark, it supports both in-memory storage
and on disk storage.
In terms of operations, Map Reduce only supports the map
and reduce operations, whereas Spark
supports Map Reduce, join, sample,
and many other operations.
The execution model for Map Reduce is limited to batch,
whereas for Spark, Spark supports
execution models including batch, interactive,
and streaming.
In terms of programming environments,
Map Reduce only supports the Java environment,
whereas Spark supports Scala, Java, R, and Python.
Other differences between Spark and Map Reduce
include Spark having support for generalized patterns.
It has a unified engine that supports many different kinds
of programming use cases.
Spark also supports lazy evaluation
of the lineage graph, which leads to reduced wait
states and better pipelining.
Spark also has a lower overhead for starting jobs
and less expensive shuffles.
Pulling all of this together, in-memory operation
makes a huge difference in terms of overall performance.
Here's a comparison of two different iterative machine
learning algorithms, K-means clustering
and logistic regression.
On the x-axis, we have the run time
of these algorithms for the different environments
in seconds.
Let's start with K-means clustering.
In red, we have Hadoop Map Reduce,
and you can see it takes 121 seconds to complete
that machine learning algorithm, whereas Spark
takes 4.1 seconds.
For logistic regression, it takes Map Reduce 80 seconds
to complete the execution, whereas Spark
completes execution in less than a second.
Here are results from the Daytona Gray
100 terabyte sort benchmark.
Spark set the record for the sort benchmark in fall of 2014
by reducing the time it took to perform
that benchmark from Hadoop, which
held the record previously at 72 minutes, down to 23 minutes.
There's no actual benchmark for it,
but Spark demonstrated the sort of 1 petabyte.
That's 1,000 terabytes worth of data
that took only 234 minutes running on 190 Amazon EC2
instances.
A different way of looking at the difference between Spark
and other tools is this survey, which
shows the median salaries for respondents
who use a given tool.
This is a survey that covered over 100 respondents
around the globe, and it showed that Spark expertise
led to higher salaries for respondents.
Now it's just a correlation here,
but that does obviously not mean causation.
However, it's an interesting observation to see.