Some of the traditional analysis tools
that we use include Unix shell commands, Pandas,
and R. One of the things that all of these tools
have in common is they all run on a single machine.
The big data problem means that data is growing faster
than computation speeds.
We have many different sources of data
and those sources of data are growing, web, mobile,
scientific.
Storage is getting cheaper.
This means people are saving more data.
And the size of storage is doubling every 18 months.
So we can save even more data.
But CPUs are not increasing in speed.
And we have many storage bottlenecks
getting data in and out of this massive storage.
Some examples of big data include Facebook's daily logs.
They're 60 terabytes in size.
Every day, they collect 60 terabytes worth of data.
The 1,000 genomes project has 200 terabytes
of human genome data.
Google's web index is estimated to be larger
than 10 petabytes of data.
Now, driving all of this is the fact
that storage has really dropped in cost.
A one terabyte disk is only $35.
But it can take three hours to read the data from the disk
or write it to the disk.
The big data problem means that a single machine can no longer
process or even hold all of the data that we want to analyze.
The only solution we have is to distribute the data
over large clusters.
Here's an example of a large cluster, one of Google's data
center that contains tens of thousands of machines.
How do we program this thing?