The hardware we have for big data
includes lots of hard drives and CPUs.
The question is how do we organize
these CPUs and hard drives?
One approach is to put them all in one big box.
This is a solution that people used in the 1990s,
but it was very expensive, because these machines were
only produced in very low volume,
and they were considered premium hardware.
And for today's big data, these machines are not big enough.
The alternative that we use for big data
today is consumer grade hardware.
It's not the gold plated servers that we put traditionally
into data centers, but rather, it's
more desktop like kinds of machines.
These machines are very easy to add in terms of capacity,
they're much cheaper for an individual CPU and disk
than traditional servers.
But they're not as reliable, and they're much harder to manage.
The trade off is we'll deal with this complexity in software
instead.
So some of the problems that we have with cheap hardware
include failures.
So Google's numbers are that you lose between 1% to 5%
of hard drives every year.
And 0.2% of memory chips per year.
Also, network speeds are much slower
than the shared memory speeds that we
found in those big box 1990s solutions.
It's much slower to read something over the network,
and the network can be much slower than reading something
from a storage drive.
Also, these machines have very uneven performance.
Some may be very fast, others may be very slow, sometimes
because they're failing.