What if we have a really large document?
Well, one approach is to take that document
and to split up into different partitions.
We can then process those partitions individually
using the same approach that we just used on a single machine
for a small document.
So here, we have four machines.
And we've taken our document and divided it up
into four partitions.
Each machine only computes the word occurrence
for that machine's partition of the document.
And then, once we're done, on the fifth machine,
we combine all of the results.
But what's the problem with this type of approach if we
have a really large document?
Well, the problem is all of the results
have to fit in one machine.
So now, machine five has to be really, really large
if we have a really, really large document
that we start with that has lots and lots of words.
So that's not a good approach.
Another alternative you might think of doing
would be to try and add layers of aggregation.
So machines one and two combine their results.
And machines three and four combine their results.
But ultimately, all of the results
still have to fit on one machine.
So this approach won't work either
for a really, really large document.
Instead, we could use Divide and Conquer.
So we're going to take our document,
partition it, and process it individually on machines one
through four.
And then, all of the machines will send their value
for their counts for I to one machine,
and their counts for do to one machine, and so on.
And we can do this for all of the words.
Partition everything across the machines.
And in fact, these could be the same machines one through four
that we used already.
Now, our result is also partitioned
across multiple machines.
This first step of counting all of the words is a Map.
Combining all of those results is a Reduce.
And this is what Google wrote about in 2004
in a research paper.