The Spark Computing Framework provides
programming abstractions and a parallel runtime
that hides the complexities of fault-tolerance and slow
machines.
Basically, all a programmer has to do is say here's
an operation, run it on all of the data.
They don't have to worry about where it runs.
That's handled by Spark.
And they don't have to worry about slow nodes or failed
nodes.
Spark will automatically run it multiple times
and guarantee the correct result.
Now, the Spark Framework actually
consists of four components.
There's the core Apache Spark component
along with Spark SQL, Spark Streaming, the ML machine
learning library, and the GraphX graphical computing library.