Data quality problems can also rise during data retrieval.
Exported data sets are often just a view of the actual data.
And problems can occur because the source
or the need for drive data was not properly understood.
Or it can just be ordinary mistakes, for example,
performing an inner join instead of an outer join,
or not understanding what null values mean.
They can also be computational constraints.
For example, producing the full history might be too expensive.
And so you supply a limited snapshot instead.
But what are the limitations of that snapshot?
Or it could be incompatibility issues, for example,
producing the data in ASCII instead of Unicode or UTF-8.
Data mining and analysis can also introduce problems.
You need to understand what you're doing with the data.
And there can be many problems that can occur
during the analysis phase.
Scale and performance issues, confidence
bounds-- understanding what they are-- black boxes
or dart boards, being attached to a model,
having insufficient domain expertise,
or applying casual empiricism-- that
is, using some arbitrary number has
to support a pre-conception.
So for retrieval and mining, there
are many potential solutions.
For data exploration, you can try
to determine which models and techniques are appropriate.
Try to find data bugs and develop domain expertise.
You should perform continuous analysis to determine,
are the results stable?
If they change, how do they change?
And it's very important to have accountability.
Make analysis part of the feedback loop.