You should use a multi-disciplinary approach
when attacking data quality problems because no one
approach will solve all of the problems.
As an example of some of the disciplines that you want
to use, they include process management--
ensuring that you have the proper procedures.
Statistics-- focusing on analysis
that you can find and repair anomalies in the data.
Database management techniques, so you
can focus on relationships to ensure consistency.
And metadata and domain expertise-- what does this data
mean, or how do you interpret this data?
The data quality issues could also
be introduced during data integration
when you're combining data sets that you've
acquired or collected across departments.
This is a very common source of problems
because oftentimes you have heterogeneous data.
There might not be a common key, or there
may be different field formats.
In this case, you may have to apply a technique called
approximate matching.
There may also be different definitions
of what is a customer.
In one data set, it may be an account.
In another data set, it might be an individual.
And in the third data set, it might be a family.
Time synchronization can also be a problem
during data integration.
Does the data relate to the same time periods,
or are the time windows compatible?
Another integration challenge is when
you have legacy data, data that's
coming from different spreadsheets
and different formats, or files with ad hoc structures.
A challenge that we have during data integration
is duplicate record detection, or DeDup.
Examples are resolving multiple different entries,
identifying what is an appropriate entity
or a matching entity, or determining
which references are correct, or which object
ID should be consolidated.
Or removing duplicates by merging or purging
values in the data set, or linking together
records spanning across different data sources,
or performing approximate matches,
where we accept fuzziness instead of an exact match.
Or householding-- this is a special case where
we try to determine things like, are different people
in the same household?
Here's an example of entity resolution.
These are two listings that we scraped
from Google and from Amazon.
Are these two listings the same product?
They appear very similar.
In fact, they are the same product.
In the lab, you'll look at an algorithmic approach
to doing entity resolution.