Let's look at some more examples of data integration.
So here's a dedup example from Bing Shopping,
and we can see we have two products here, Apple iPad 2s.
And it turns out these are actually the same product,
but they haven't been merged together when we see the list,
even though they should actually be merged together.
Another example is to take your data sets
and convert the entries in the data sets
into a canonical form.
The example here is the US Postal Service
provides guidelines for canonicalizing mailing
addresses.
By converting a mailing address to a canonical form,
we can try and determine whether two addresses are actually
the same address.
In general, we can apply very sophisticated techniques
during the data integration process
to detect duplicates or other problems.
We can use evidence from multiple fields,
both as positive examples that two things
are identical or negative examples
that they are separate.
We can also use evidence from linkage patterns
with other records, and we can apply
clustering-based approaches.
Again, there are more sophisticated techniques
that we can apply here.
But there are lots of additional problems
that we can run into during the integration process.
Are things stored as addresses, or as number, street, and city?
What are the units that are used?
And how do we deal with merging together
two data sets that have different units
or different constraints, both static and dynamic?
Or how do we deal with the fact that there
may be multiple versions that we're trying to combine,
or a schema that may have changed over time?
Or dealing with other metadata in addition to the data
that we're trying to merge?
All of these are issues that we have to worry about.
Now, in terms of solutions to the data integration problem,
there are commercial tools based on a significant body
of research in data integration.
And there are many tools for dealing
with problems such as address matching or schema mapping
that you can use.
There are also data browsing and exploration tools
These can help you identify the many hidden problems that
may happen when you're trying to merge together
or integrate in new data.
You can also view the before and after results and see,
did you get the intended results when you
integrated in a new data set?