Data cleaning helps to deal with missing data.
For example, one censor data set might have humidity
while the other does not.
Data cleaning also helps to deal with entity resolution,
so for example, the difference between IBM
versus International Business Machines.
It also helps to deal with unit mismatch.
For example, in one data set, you might have dollars.
In another, you might have pounds, and so on.
Now, the statistics view of how you deal with data that's dirty
is that there's a process that produces data,
and we want to model ideal samples from that process.
But in practice, we have non-ideal samples.
That's because of distortion-- some samples
are corrupted by a process.
Selection bias-- the likelihood of a sample
depends on its value.
And left and right censorship, where
we have users that come and go from our scrutiny.
So censors, for example, that enter
our data set at some point and then leave our data set.
And dependence-- samples that are supposed to be independent
but are not.
So for example, in social networks,
individuals within a social network
are not necessarily independent.
So we can add models for each type of imperfection,
but the challenge is we can't model everything.
So we have to think about what's the best
trade-off between accuracy and simplicity.
From the database point of view with dirty data is as follows.
So I've got my hands on this data set.
Some of the values are missing, or corrupted, or wrong,
or duplicated.
But results are absolute because we have this relational model.
And so we get a better answer by improving the quality
of values in the data set.
The domain expert's view of dirty data
is that this data doesn't look right,
or this answer doesn't look right.
So they want to understand what happened.
And domain experts have an inclusive model of the data
that they can test against.
A data scientist's view is some combination of all of the above
when they're looking at dirty data.