Where do data quality problems come from?
Many places.
For example, the source data could be dirty on its own,
or transformations that you apply to the data
could corrupt the data.
And this is a challenge with the complexity of the software
pipelines that we build process data for data science.
We can also have clean data sets that are screwed up
because of the integration, where
we combine multiple data sets together
and do that incorrectly.
Things that are rare errors can become frequent errors
after we perform a transformation or integration.
And even a clean data set can suffer
from bit rot-- that's data that loses either its value
or accuracy over time.
Or any combination of the above can
cause data quality problems.
So again, looking at the big picture,
where does dirty data come from?
It can come from the extract, transform,
and load process, where we have to deal with integrating data
from multiple different data sources, such as application
databases, files, and logs.
We need to clean this data when we move it
into our data warehouse.