There are many different types of dirty data problems
that we can run into.
For example, parsing the text from a text file into fields
may have trouble because there are different issues
with the separators.
The naming conventions that we use
can also cause problems with entity recognition.
For example, abbreviating New York City as NYC.
We may have missing information, like a required
field-- for example, a key field that we're
using for tabular data.
We also may have violations of what's
called the primary key in a database, when
we move from unstructured to structured data,
or when we're trying to integrate additional data
into our database.
We may have licensing or privacy issues
that prevent us from using data the way that we'd like to.
We may have different representations for data.
Some people may refer to the data as "2" numerically,
or others written out as "t-w-o."
Fields maybe too long and truncated
during the integration process.
We may have duplicate or redundant records
that are exact matches or approximate matches
for each other that we have to detect and remove.
We also may have formatting issues.
Formatting issues are particularly
a problem when we're dealing with dates,
as there are multiple different representations that we
can use.
Consider, for example, European versus American representations
of dates.
There are many meanings of data quality, and many uses of data.
We can use data for operations, or for aggregate analysis
or for customer relations.
These are all very different ways of using the data,
with different requirements on data quality.
There are also different interpretations
that we may have for data based upon the quality of the data.
If we don't understand all the rules behind the data,
it might actually be useless to have the data.
Then there's the question of data suitability.
Can we get the answer that we want from the available data?
We may have proxy data that's approximating
the data that we're looking at, or we
may be missing the important, relevant data that we
need to make a decision.
Data quality spans a continuum, and data and information
are not static.
Data flows in a data collection and usage process
through multiple stages.
We gather the data, we deliver the data,
we store the data-- perhaps for a long time.
We integrate together multiple different data sets,
we retrieve data, and then we perform mining and analysis.
We're going to go through each of these steps in this lecture.