Data quality issues could also be introduced
during data delivery-- for example,
destroying, mutilating information
through bad preprocessing.
As examples, inappropriate aggregation
or incorrectly converting null values into default values.
It can also happen due to the loss
of data-- say from a buffer overflow or transmission
problem, or a lack of integrity checks.
Potential solutions to the data delivery problem
are to build reliable transmission protocols.
Use a relay server to store data and verify it
before it's inserted into the data set.
Use checksums or a verification parser for verification.
Determine does the uploaded file actually fit
the expected pattern?
Examine the relationships.
These are the dependencies between data streams
and preprocessing steps.
And ask your data supplier to provide you
with a commitment around the quality of data
that they're providing.