Data quality problems can be introduced during data storage.
So you have a data set.
What do you do with it?
You store it.
But there can be problems in the physical storage of that data.
Now, this is a potential issue, but storage is cheap.
And so we should store redundantly as an example.
So some of problems that we can run into in storage
are logical, for example, having poor metadata.
So when we have data feeds that are
derived from programs or legacy sources, what does it mean?
If we don't understand what the metadata is for these programs,
we can't understand what the quality of the data is.
Also, having an inappropriate data model
is a problem if you don't have the right timestamps
or the correct normalization of the data.
Or if you make ad-hoc modifications to the data,
changing the structure, for example,
to fit the graphical user interface that you
use to explore the data.
Or if you have hardware or software constraints.
For example, transmitting the data via Excel spreadsheets
or running into Y2K, Year 2000 problems,
because you chose to use two-digit years instead
of four-digit years.
Potential solutions are to make sure
that you document and publish the data specifications.
Track that metadata very carefully.
Good planning can also help.
Assume that everything bad will happen and then plan for it.
This can be very difficult, however,
to anticipate all of the potential problems.
Also consider using data exploration.
Browse the data or use data mining tools
to examine the data and make sure
that it meets the specifications that you've assumed
or to determine, has something changed that you didn't expect?