This is a cautionary tale about performing data science.
In 1958 Ancel Keys started the Seven Countries Study
where he followed 13,000 subjects for anywhere
from five to 40 years.
Now as a part of this study, he produced the following graph.
This graph shows on the x-axis the fat calories
consumed as a percentage of total daily calories consumed.
On the y-axis it shows deaths per 1,000
for degenerative heart disease.
And this is for the time period 1948 to 1949 for men.
What you can see here is that it appears
to be that it's the case that there's
a correlation between the fat calories consumed
and deaths per 1,000 from degenerative heart disease.
However, this study has caused a lot of controversy.
In particular, he only studied a subset of the 21 countries
that had data.
He also failed to consider other factors that
might cause deaths from degenerative heart disease.
For example, if we look at the per capita annual sugar
consumption in pounds, we find that for Japan it was
15 pounds per person per year.
In Italy it was 40 pounds per person per year.
And in England and Wales it was 60 pounds per person per year.
So appears here that there's a correlation between per capita
annual sugar consumption in pounds,
and deaths per 1,000 of degenerative heart disease.
So this really emphasizes the point
that Fisher made that correlation does not
imply causation.