Let's look at several examples of why
there's so much excitement around working with big data.
The first is nowcasting.
Traditionally what people have done is forecasting.
You collect a bunch of data, you build a model,
and you use that model to predict the future.
With nowcasting, you collect a lot of data
and you build a model, but instead you
use it to predict what's happening now.
So the example we're going to use is Google Flu trends.
The way that traditionally we determine
that there's an outbreak of the flu
is when someone's ill they go to the doctor,
the doctor fills out an incident report
and passes that on to their local health department, which
then passes it up the hierarchy through the county, the state.
Eventually it reaches the Centers
for Disease Control in Atlanta, Georgia.
That process takes about two weeks,
so it takes a roughly two weeks to know that there's
an outbreak of flu, by which time
the outbreak may actually already be over.
With Google Flu Trends, what Google did is
they started with lots of data.
From 2003 to 2008, they looked at weekly search queries.
There's about 50 million of these.
From the search queries, they were
able to derive 45 terms that were relevant to people
who are searching for flu information
when they had the flu.
They used this to build a model.
The model was very accurate.
In February of 2010 it was able to detect an outbreak
two weeks ahead of CDC data.
Initially the model was about 97% accurate,
but during the period from 2011 to 2013,
it overestimated the prevalence of flu,
including an interval in the 2012 to 2013
period where it was off by a factor of two.
That is, Google Flu Trends estimated
that there were twice as many flu cases
as there actually were.
So what happened?
What happened is Google rolled out flu stories in Google News
during this period.
And so now people started reading about flu in the news
and searching on those stories, either
for those stories or things in those stories,
and that skewed their results.
Once they identified those factors,
they were able to take them into account
and the model was very accurate after that.
And in fact today new types of models
are being used to estimate which cities are most
at risk for the spread of the Ebola virus.