Let's look at another cautionary tale
around performing data science.
So in 2014, Princeton University researchers
published a paper titled, "An Epidemiological
Modeling of Online Social Network Dynamics."
The paper made quite a splash, because the last sentence
of the abstract was, quote, "extrapolating the best fit
model into the future predicts a rapid decline
in Facebook activity in the next few years."
Wow.
They're predicting that Facebook as we
know it won't exist anymore in just a few years.
How did they come to this conclusion?
They looked at Google Trends searches for Myspace.
And here on the left you see two different graphs
showing the results of the prevalence of Google Trends
searches over time and can see that there's
a peak in 2008, followed by a decline in the searches.
They fitted two different models to this decline
and then repeated that same process
with Google Trends searches for Facebook.
So here, you see the trends peak in 2012, followed by a decline.
They use that to then apply the same model
that they had derived from Myspace to predict
the future number of trends for Facebook.
And they arrive at the conclusion
that since there are going to be no more searches for Facebook
in just a few years, there'll be no more
Facebook in just a few years.
So Facebook researchers saw this, and they had to respond,
of course, firmly tongue in cheek.
And they put the following blog post with the following
conclusion, which is "in keeping with the scientific principle
'correlation equals causation,' our research unequivocally
demonstrated that Princeton may be in danger of disappearing
entirely."
So how did they arrive at this conclusion?
They looked at the proportion of total page likes
for Princeton, Harvard, and Yale.
In The.
Graph on the bottom, we can see that there's
a steady increase in total page lakes for Yale,
with a slight decrease in 2014.
Harvard shows substantial growth up until about 2012,
and then there's a declining trend.
But Princeton shows a sharp decline from 2009 to 2010,
with a slight recovery from 2010 to 2014,
and then a slight decline.
Looking at this Princeton search trends,
they extrapolate that this trend suggests
that Princeton will have only half of its current enrollment
by 2018.
And by 2021, it will have no students at all.
Now, of course, since all of this
was tongue in cheek in terms of the response,
they went further.
And they say, "While we're concerned for Princeton
University, we are even more concerned
about the fate of the planet, because Google Trends for 'air'
have also been climbing steadily,
and our projection show that by the year 2060,
there we know air left at all."
And they produce this graph of interest over time in air.