Now that we have VirtualBox and Vagrant installed,
we're going to go and download the box.
So first off, what we basically have to do
is download a zip file that's going
to contain a Vagrant file, a file which is what we require
to interact with Vagrant.
Here's the address here of the zip file
that we need to go get.
Github.com/spark mooc/mooc setup/archive/master.zip
We're going to choose to save the file.
Now, I'm going to open a terminal.
My file has downloaded into my downloads folder.
I'm going to unzip it here.
So we see a Vagrant file, and also a VM
test student IPython notebook which
will be used at a later time.
So what I'm going to be doing here
is just create some folder.
It's your choice, I'm just going to call it myvagrant.
And then I will CD into that directory,
and I will copy the Vagrant file.
Oh, sorry.
It's actually in downloads, mooc set up master vagrant.
I'm going to copy that file here, typo.
So now I have my vagrant file here.
From this point, I simply need to do a Vagrant up.
And this will go and download the box with the spark
that I need.
And it's-- I've edited the video a bit here,
so it did take several minutes for the whole download
and everything to happen, but I've edited the video just
to remove that so you're not necessarily sitting here
waiting.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm just
going to go up here, go to VirtualBox.
OK, so what we see here is a Spark VM VM, and it's running.