We're just going to go through a few basic commands
for using the box.
Going through Vagrant and using the proper commands
ensures, or should ensure that your virtual machine remains
stable and usable.
If you use any other methods or do not
do clean shutdowns of the virtual machine,
unexpected things could happen.
So first off, I'm going to open up VirtualBox
so we can see it running here in the background.
Here I see my virtual machine is powered off.
Open up a terminal.
Put it in the foreground, kind of over here.
CD into my directory, my custom directory, my vagrant,
and to just simply start the virtual machine or the box,
do a Vagrant up.
It'll take a little bit here, but it will start.
You can see what's going on here,
there's a preview screen here.
And we'll also get some feedback immediate here,
command line, once it's actually done starting up.
So it's started.
To do a clean shutdown, or clean stop of my virtual machine
we'd do a vagrant halt. OK, that's the command to run,
and that should be the command that you basically
run every time you're going to possibly shut down
your desktop, your system server, or what have you.
There's also a Vagrant destroy, which will basically remove
the virtual machine completely.
So it would actually remove this virtual machine here
completely, if I did a destroy, which I'm not going to do.
OK, so I'm going to leave it running, minimize.
So now we're going to go-- not that we have the box running,
we're going to go to our Python notebook that should be running
within the virtual machine.
So the special port to access it, an address,
127.0.0.1:80001.
And there we go, our Python notebook.