Looking at file performance when we're using compression,
here we have a table that shows the performance
when using the Scala and Java languages.
The upper table shows a binary file, that 787 megabyte file.
The lower table shows the text file, 626 megabytes in size.
Now, for each of these files, we look
at performance for raw I/O, versus using
LZ4 with the fast setting, versus using Gzip
with different levels of compression.
Now, the first thing that we can observe
when we look at this table is that write times are
much larger than read times.
That is, it takes much longer to write a compressed file
than to read a compressed file.
The second observation we can make
is that there's a large range of compression times.
So Gzip level one only takes 14 seconds to write,
whereas Gzip level six takes 75 seconds to write.
The next observation we can make is
that different compression schemes, LZ4 versus Gzip,
also have different times.
So it's only four seconds for LZ4 compression,
which is less than even Gzip level one compression.
The next observation is that there's a very small range
of compressed file sizes.
Ranging from 328 megabytes to 286,
is only a 15% range of compression,
even though the time varies from 14 seconds to 75 seconds
to write, and they have the same read times.
We also observe that binary I/O is still
much faster than text-based I/O, so four seconds for LZ4 verses
24 seconds for LZ4 with a text file.
The same thing for reading.
Reading is much faster with a binary file,
2 seconds versus 22 seconds for the text file.
Another interesting observation is
that LZ4 compression is very close to the raw I/O speed.
So only four seconds for writing versus a range of one
to six seconds for writing the raw file.
The same thing is true for doing reading.
Reading is only two seconds using
LZ4, verses one to six seconds for the binary file.
In summary, uncompressed read and write times are comparable.
Binary I/O is much faster than text I/O.
And compressed reads are much faster than compressed writes.
Using LZ4, in this case, is better than using Gzip.
And LZ4 compression times approach the raw I/O times.