So in review, the big picture is we have a data warehouse,
and from that data warehouse we'd
like to extract data products, analytics,
and business intelligence.
We get information into the data warehouse
by performing extract, transform, and load operations
on application databases, files, and logs.
Now, some of the key data management
concepts that we want to consider are a data model.
This is a collection of concepts for describing
data and a schema, which is a description
of a particular collection of data using a given data model.
Now, information spans a structure spectrum,
ranging from unstructured, or schema-never data.
This is information that has no structure
and never will have structure.
It includes things like plain text and media.
Semi-structured, or structure-later data,
includes things like documents, Extensible Markup Language
content, and tag text, or media.
The last structure element is structured data,
and this is schema-first data.
This includes things like relational databases
and formatted messages.
Today, we will look at semi-structured data
or schema-later data, where we apply a schema
after we create that data.