Files are named sequence of bytes.
They're typically stored as a collection of pages or blocks.
A file system is a collection of files
organized within a hierarchical namespace.
And a file system is responsible for laying out
those bytes on physical media, storing the file metadata,
and providing an application programming interface
for interaction with files.
API operations include open, close, seek, read, and write.
Now, files are organized in a hierarchical namespace.
In Linux, forward slash is the root of a file system.
And on Windows, backslash is the root of a file system.
Files and directories have associated permissions,
but it's important to recognize that files are not always
necessarily arranged in a hierarchical namespace.
For example, in content addressable storage,
which is often used for large multimedia collections,
we refer to the content by its content,
not necessarily by its hierarchical name.
Now, some considerations for a file format
are, what are the data models?
Is it tabular, hierarchical or array?
What is the physical layout?
What are the field units and validation?
What metadata do we need to store?
For example, header, or side file, or specification,
or other information.
What types of data do we want to store in the files?
Are they plain text or binary files?
What do we use as delimiters for fields?
And how do we escape special content or characters?
Are the files compressed or do they use encryption?
Or do we have checksums that we can
use to validate that the files have not
been tampered with or damaged?
And finally, how do we evolve the format or the schema
for the file?