Semi-structured tabular data is one of the most common data
formats.
A table is a collection of rows and columns.
Each row has an index, and each column has a name.
A cell is specified by an index name pair.
And a cell may or may not have a value.
The type of a cell is inferred from its value.
Here's an example of tabular data.
This is Fortune 500 companies.
These are the top 500 US closely held
and public corporations by gross revenue.
What you can see from this table is that there are different
columns,-- for example, rank, company name, revenue--
and there are different rows for each company that's in this
tabular data.
Now, we can take and export this data as a comma separated value
file.
That file looks like this.
And it consists of a header row that
consists of the columns separated by commas, the column
names, and then rows consisting of values
for each one of those columns separated by commas.
Each company is on a different row.
Here's a different exported file.
This is from a protein data bank.
And here the format is different.
The format is the first column of a line is the field
name followed by values.
And field names can be repeated on multiple lines.