pandas is an open source data analysis and modeling library
that's an alternative to using R. pandas provides
data frames, which are a table with named columns.
It's the most commonly used pandas object.
And it's represented as a Python dictionary that
maps column names to series.
Each pandas series object represents a column.
And you can think of it as a one-dimensional labeled
array that's capable of holding any data type.
R also has a similar data frame type.
Spark introduced DataFrames in Spark 1.3
as an extension to RDDs.
They're a distributed collection of data that's
organized into named columns.
So they're equivalent pandas in R DataFrames,
but they're distributed.
And the types of columns are inferred from values.
It's very easy to convert between pandas and pySpark
DataFrames.
One important consideration, however,
is that when you convert from a Spark DataFrame
to a pandas DataFrame, you have to make sure
that that pandas Data, Frame will
fit in the driver's memory.
Here's the code that you would use
to convert the Spark DataFrame into a pandas DataFrame
and to create a Spark DataFrame from pandas DataFrame.
As you can see, it's very straightforward and easy to do.
The performance difference between using DataFrames
and RDDs is significance.
Here is a graph that shows the performance
of aggregating 10 million integer
pairs in seconds on the x-axis.
And it shows the performance in blue,
RDDs using Python and Scala bindings and, in green,
performance using Python and Scala bindings with DataFrames.
And you can see that performance with DataFrames
is almost five times better than the performance
using RDDs for pySpark.
So when you have a choice between using DataFrames
and using RDDs for large data, you're better off
using DataFrames in most cases.