Here's an example of a system log file from a machine.
And you can see that there are multiple applications running
on this machine.
And you can also see some of the system operations
that are happening on this machine.
Now, we can collect these types of files from many machines
and then check them for unusual events, like disk
errors, network congestion, or security attacks.
We can also monitor the resources on the machines
from these files, looking at things
like the network, the memory, the disc, the CPU,
or application queues.
We can take all of that information,
and we can visualize it with a dashboard.
So for example, here us a dashboard
from Splunk, which provides a free version of its Enterprise
software that you can download and try with your own data.