In this segment, we'll talk about linear classification
and relate it to the problem of linear regression.
We'll also introduce logistic regression,
which is a particular type of linear classification model.
As a reminder, classification is a supervised learning setting.
And our goal is to learn a mapping from observations
to discreet labels given a set of training examples.
Spam classification is a canonical example
of classification where the observations are emails
and the labels are spam and not spam.
Given a set of label to emails, we
want to predict whether a new email is spam or not spam.
Click-through rate prediction is another example.
Here, our observations are user and publisher triples.
Our labels are not-click and click.
And given a set of labeled observations,
we want to predict whether a new user ad publisher triple
will result in a click.
In fact, we really want to predict this
at a more granular level using probabilities.
But we'll discuss that in later segments.
In this segment, we're interested in
linear classification models.
And to develop our understanding,
we'll start with a review of linear regression.
In linear regression, our key assumption
is that there's a linear mapping between the features
and the label.
Assuming we have three features represented by x1, x2, and x3,
this means that we assume that we can define y
as a weighted sum of these features
plus some offset value, which we denote by w0.
Additionally, to account for this offset value,
we can augment our feature vector
by adding an additional feature that
equals 1 for all observations.
And then we can rewrite this linear mapping assumption
as a scalar or inner product.
As we previously discussed, using a linear mapping
is attractive for several reasons.
First, it is intuitive and mathematically simple.
Second, it often works well in practice.
And finally, we have the flexibility
to introduce new features as we like.
And we can thus increase the complexity
of this model via the process of feature extraction.
So the natural question is how can we extend these ideas
to the classification setting.
Let's assume we're trying to predict whether or not
it will rain given three weather related
features, in particular, temperature, cloudiness,
and humidity.
We can use the same feature representation, as
with linear regression, including the one feature
to multiply by an offset.
But now we need to figure out how
we can make class predictions.
In particular, we'll be focusing in binary classification.
So we want our predictions to ultimately be binary,
for example, not rain versus rain, not spam versus spam,
not click versus click.
To achieve this goal, we can't directly
use the linear regression model since linear regression
predictions are real values rather than class predictions.
But we can get around this issue by thresholding
the linear regression prediction.
So recall that the linear regression prediction is simply
the dot product between the parameter
vector and the feature vector.
And we can set our classification prediction
to be the sine of this dot product.
What this rule says is that a w transpose x is positive,
then our prediction y hat is 1.
And a w transpose x is negative, our prediction is negative 1.
And when w transpose x equals 0, we
can arbitrarily choose the prediction
to be 1 or negative 1.
Another way to say this is that w transpose x equals 0
is our decision boundary.
Now let's look at an example to better understand
what's going on.
Imagine we have two features.
And we are given a linear classifier.
This classifier puts weight of 3 on the first feature and weight
of negative 4 on the second feature.
And it has an offset of negative 1.
So how how does this linear classifier make predictions?
Imagine we have a test point whose first feature equals 2
and whose second feature equals 3,
as is shown in the graph on the left of the screen.
Also recall that we represent our point as a three
dimensional vector with the first component
of the vector equaling 1 to correspond
with the offset in the linear model.
Now, to compute our prediction, we simply
take the dot product between our feature vector and our model.
And we look at the sine of this resulting number.
In our example, the dot product equals 7, which is negative.
And thus, the prediction is negative 1.
We'll denote the label as being negative 1
by coloring the point red in the graph on the left.
We can do something similar with a second test point
whose first feature equals 2 and whose second feature equals 1.
This time, the dot product of the feature vector
and the model is positive.
So the label is 1.
And we color the point blue in the graph on the left.
We can follow this procedure for two more arbitrary test points,
visualizing them with the appropriate color based
on the sine of their dot products.
And if we repeat this exercise several more times,
a pattern starts to emerge.
In particular, we note that all points
on one side of the decision boundary are red.
And all points on the other side are blue.
This decision boundary is defined by the equation w
transpose x equals 0.
So now we figured out how to adapt the linear regression
scheme to return class predictions.
But a related question is how do we evaluate these predictions.
In the regression setting, we were dealing with real value
predictions where we had some notion of closeness
between the label and the prediction.
So squared loss was a natural metric for evaluation.
However, in the classification setting,
our class labels are discreet.
And perhaps the most intuitive thing we can do
is to simply check whether the label and the prediction
are equal.
If they match, then we'll incur no penalty, or no loss.
And if they differ, we'll incur a loss equal to 1.
And this is what we call by the 0-1 loss.
So let's see what this looks like visually.
And to do this, we need to introduce some notation.
Remember that we're defining our labels
to be either negative 1 or 1.
Additionally, our predicted label
is determined by the sine of w transpose x.
Hence, if our prediction matches the true label,
then either y is positive and w transpose x is positive.
Or y is negative and w transpose x is negative.
In both cases, the product of y times w
transpose x will be positive.
In contrast, when the true and predicted labels don't match,
this product must be negative.
So we can define z to equal this product.
And when z is positive, we have a good prediction.
And when z is negative, we have a bad prediction.
Having defined z, we can now visualize the 0-1 loss, which
looks like a step function.
Whenever z is greater than 0, we incur no loss.
And whenever z is negative, we incur a constant loss of 1.
So now we seem to have all the pieces in place
to learn a model.
Specifically, as before, we're making a linear assumption
using the sign of a dot product as our prediction.
And we're using the 0-1 loss to evaluate these predictions.
So given a set of end training points,
we then want to find a parameter vector
w that minimizes the 0-1 loss over our training points.
Unfortunately, this is not a convex optimization problem
as a 0-1 loss is not a convex function.
And thus, this is a hard problem to solve.
But all hope isn't lost, because instead of using the 0-1 loss
in our optimization problem, we can use a surrogate loss that
is convex and also provides a good approximation to 0-1 loss.
There are many potential surrogate losses
that we can choose from.
For instance, the hinge loss is used to define the SVM model.
The exponential loss is used to describe the Adaboost model.
And the logistic loss is used to define the logistic regression
model.
In particular, we'll focus on logistic regression
and on the logistic or log loss.
By replacing the 0-1 loss with the logistic loss
in the previous optimization problem,
we can now define the logistic regression optimization
problem.
The goal in logistic regression is
to find a linear model that minimizes
the sum of the logistic losses over the training points.
Unlike linear regression, this problem
has no closed form solution.
But it is a convex optimization problem.
And as a result, a standard method
for solving logistic regression is via gradient descent.
We use the same high level update rule
as we did for linear regression.
But of course, the form of the gradient
is different because we're using a different loss function.
The specific form of the update is
shown on the bottom right of the slide.
Finally, similar to ridge regression,
we can use a regularized version of logistic regression.
In this regularized version, we're
trading off between two terms.
The first is the log loss on the training data.
And the second is the model complexity.
As in the case of ridge regression,
we introduce a user specified hyper parameter, lambda,
to determine the trade-off between these two terms.