Broadcast variables allow us to keep a read-only variable
cached at a worker.
We can send it to the worker only once instead
of having to send it with each task
that we perform at that worker.
As an example, we could efficiently give every worker
a large data set or table.
Now usually, broadcast variables are
distributed using very efficient broadcast algorithms.
Using broadcast variables is very straightforward.
At the driver you simply use Spark Context dot broadcast
to specify the broadcast variable.
And at a worker, in the code that's automatically
passed via a closure, you simply refer to that broadcast
variable with dot value.
Here's an example of using a broadcast variable
for country code lookup for HAM radio call signs.
So we have an RDD, contactCounts,
that contains a list of call signs and the number of times
that we've seen each call sign.
So it's a pair of call sign and account.
And we want to look up the country code associated
with that call sign.
So we create a table, called signPrefixes,
that contains this information.
We then create a function, processSignCounts,
which will take in one of these pairs of a call sign
and a number of times that it's been seen along
with that table, signPrefixes, and we'll
look up the country code from the first element
of the pair, the call sign.
And then return a pair consisting
of the country and the number of times
that we've seen that call sign.
Now, we can apply this to our contactCounts RDD using a map
function where we pass in this function that we just defined,
processSignCounts.
What that'll do is when that runs,
Spark will automatically create a closure containing
processSignCount along with signPrefixes--
that large table that we just created--
and send that to the worker.
If we now want to process a second contactCounts RDD,
it'll repeat that process all over again of constructing
the closure of the function along with this large call sign
table.
So that can be very expensive if this table is very, very
large because it's being sent every time we process the file.
As an alternative, all we have to do
is add the Spark Context dot broadcast to our load call sign
table to create a broadcast variable.
And then when we want to invoke it,
we just simply use signPrefixes.value.
Now, our table is only sent once to the workers
and will be reused every time we want to look up
a different contactCounts RDD.