Accumulators are variables that could only be added
to by an associative operation.
They're used to very efficiently implement parallel counters
and sums, and only the driver can read an accumulator's
values, not the tasks.
Here's an example.
We create an accumulator and set the value to zero.
We then take an rdd, consisting of one, two, three, and four,
and we're going to run a for each function against it, that
will apply the function to each of those elements.
And it'll do that at the workers.
The function we define is to take the accumulator
and add the value to that accumulator.
When we run this, we can then see
that the value of the accumulator will be 10.
Because at each worker, we will add the value of the element.
In this case, we start with one at the first worker,
two at the second worker, three at the third worker,
and four at the fourth worker.
Each of those adds up to 10.
Here's an example where we're going
to count empty lines in a file.
So we start by creating an rdd from that text file.
And we have an accumulator that is set to zero.
Now, we're going to extract call signs from that file,
and we're going to reference the accumulator blank lines.
And if the line is empty, we're going
to add 1 to that accumulator.
Otherwise, we're going to return the value
of splitting that line.
Now we can take and create a new rdd call signs by flat mapping
that file rdd that we created by passing in the rdd function,
extract call signs.
Each time extract call signs runs against an element,
if the element is blank, it's going to add one.
If it's not, it'll return the value of splitting the line.
Flat map will then turn that into separate elements.
At the end, we can print out the accumulator at the driver
blank lines, and we'll see what the value is.
Now, tasks at workers cannot access an accumulator's value.
Task C accumulators as write only variables.
And accumulators can be used in actions or in transformations.
In an action, each tasks update to the accumulator
is guaranteed by spark to only be applied once.
When you perform transformations,
there's no guarantee because a transformation
might have to be run multiple times
if there are slow nodes or a node fails.
So you should only use accumulators
for debugging purposes when you have transformations.
Accumulators support the types integers,
double, long, and float, and you can also create accumulators
with custom types.
We use one of those in one of the labs.