Resilient distributed datasets are the primary abstraction
in Spark.
They are immutable once you create an RDD.
You cannot change IT.
You can transform it.
You can perform actions on it.
But you cannot change an RDD once you construct it.
Spark tracks lineage information to enable
the efficient recomputation of any lost data
if a machine should fail or crash.
It also enables operations on collections
of elements in parallel.
Now you can construct RDDs by paralyzing
existent Python collections such as lists,
or by transforming an existing RDD,
or from files in HDFS, or any other storage system.
A programmer specifies the number of partitions for an RDD
.
And there's a default value that's
used if you don't specify the number that you
want to be used.
Here we have an example of an RDD
that's split into five partitions.
The more partitions that you split an RDD into,
the more opportunities you have for parallelism.
So this RDD is split into five.
And those are placed onto three worker machines.
Since there's only three worker machines,
some of the worker machines have two partitions,
and one has one partition.
There are two types of operations
you can perform on an RDD-- transformations and actions.
Transformations are lazily evaluated.
They're not computed immediately.
A transformed RDD is executed only when an action runs on it.
You can also persist, or cache, RDDs in memory or on disk.
To work with RDDs, you first create an RDD
from a data source, a file, or a list.
You then apply transformations to that RDD.
So examples are map and filter.
You then apply actions to that RDD.
Examples are collect and count.
So here we have a figure that shows starting with a list,
we parallelize that list.
That creates an RDD.
We then filter that RDD, creating a new filtered RDD.
Then we do a map transformation that maps
that RDD to a new mapped RDD.
And finally, we perform a collect action,
which now causes the parallelize, the filter,
and the map transformations to actually
be executed, and return a result back to the driver machine.
Here are two reference URLs for working with Spark.
The first is a programming guide.
And the second is the PySpark API.
These are very good references when you're
developing Spark applications.
The programming guide gives you some best practices
and also cautions you against doing certain things.
The Python API is very useful if you're
wondering, is there a transformation
to do a particular operation, and also what are
the different parameters that a given
transformation or action takes.