Spark transformations enable us to create new data sets
from an existing one.
Again, we're using lazy evaluations.
That means that results are not computed right away.
Instead, what happens is Spark remembers
the set of transformations that are applied to a base data set.
It can then optimize the required calculations
and automatically recover from failures and slow workers.
The way to think about this is we're creating a recipe
for creating a result.
So let's look at some examples of transformations.
There's the map transformation, the filter, distinct,
and flatMap transformations.
The map transformation returns a new distributed data set
that's formed by passing each element of the source
through a function.
Filter returns a new data set that's
formed by selecting those elements of the source on which
the function returns true.
And the distinct transformation returns a new data set
that contains the distinct elements of the source data
set.
The flatMap transformation is similar to map,
but each input element can be mapped to zero or more output
elements.
So this means that your function should return a sequence rather
than a single item.