Recall that we've talked about two key data management
concepts.
The first being a data model, which
is a collection of concepts for describing data.
The second is a schema, which provides
a description of the particular collection of the data using
a given data model.
Now, conventional wisdom is that only 20% of data is structured.
And even this number is decreasing
because of the rise of consumer applications, enterprise
search, and media applications.
All of these generate data that is primarily
semi-structured or unstructured.
In this lecture, we will look at structured data
where we have a specific specified
schema that we start with.
And then we look at the data itself.
In a relational database, we have the following definitions.
First of all, a relational database is a set of relations.
And there are two parts to a relation-- a schema that
specifies the name of the relation
plus each column's name and type.
So here we have a schema for a relation called Students.
And it consists of columns of a sid name, email, age, and GPA.
And each of those columns has an associated type.
For example, the name is type String.
The GPA is type Real.
The second part to a relation is an instance.
And this is the actual data at any given time.
And this has two characteristics.
The first is the cardinality or the number of rows.
And the second is the degree or number
of fields in that instance.
Now, we can add to our key data management concepts
a third concept, which is a relational data model.
And this is the most used data model.
A relation is a table with rows and columns.
And every relation has a schema that defines
the fields in the columns.
The database is a large, organized collection of data.
And transactions are used to modify that data.
Databases model real world, like enterprises.
And so we have things like entities,
such as teams and games, and relationships in a database.
So we can say, for example, the entity A
plays against the entity B in the World Cup,
where "plays against" is the relationship.