Here are some examples of large databases.
The United States Internal Revenue Service
has a database consisting of 150 terabytes worth of taxpayer
records.
The Australian Bureau of Statistics
has over 250 terabytes worth of vital statistics
about Australians.
And AT&T has over 312 terabytes worth of call records
for all of its callers.
eBay's database, its largest database,
is over 1.4 petabytes in size.
And Yahoo has a click database that's
used for behavioral tracking that contains over two
petabytes worth of data.
Now, for each of these large databases,
we can ask the question, what matters for these databases?
In the case of the IRS, they care
about accuracy, consistency, durability, and the ability
to make rich queries.
The Australian Bureau of Statistics
cares about fast, rich queries.
AT&T, for their call records database,
cares about accuracy, consistency, and durability.
eBay and Yahoo care about availability and timeliness
for their databases.