Spark supports joins in two ways.
SparkSQL and Spark DataFrames support inner, outer,
left outer, right outer, and semijoin operations.
For Pair RDDs, pySpark supports inner join, left outer join,
right outer join, and full outer join.
Here's an example of how pair RDDs support joins.
X.join(Y) will return an RDD containing all pairs
of elements with matching keys in X and Y.
Each pair will be of the form k and v1, v2 as a tuple,
where (k, v1) is in X and (k, v2) is in Y.
So here we have an example of two collections,
we have a collection that contains a and y as a pair,
along with b and 4 as a pair.
And a second collection that contains a and 2 as a pair
and a and three as a pair.
When we perform a join, the result
will be a collection consisting of a and the pair 1, 2,
because 1 appears in x and 2 appears in y.
And a and the pair 1 and 3, because a 1 appears
in x and a 3 appears in y.
Notice that b does not appear in the output,
because b only appears an x not in y.
Here we have a left outer join, which
has the property that for each element kv in X,
the resulting RDD will contain either all pairs k
and the pair (v, w) for w in Y or the pair k and (v, none)
if no elements in Y have the key k.
So as the example, we have a and 1
as a pair and b and 4 as a pair.
And we have a relation consisting of a and 2
as a pair.
So when we do the left outer join,
the result will be the pair a the pair 1,
2, because 1 appears in X and 2 appears in Y with a.
And the pair b along with 4 and none, because 4 comes from X.
And b only appears in X and not in Y.
With a right outer join, each element (k, w) in Y
will result in RDD containing all pairs of k
and the pair (v, w) for v and x, or the pair k and (None, w)
if no elements in X have the key k.
So in this case, we start with a and 1 as a pair and b and four
as a pair in X. And a and 2 as a pair in Y.
Now when we perform our left outer join,
we'll end up with the result a and 2,
1, because 2 appears in Y and 1 appears
in X, both with a, and b along with (None, 4),
because b appears in X but not in Y.
The last join is a full outer join,
and for each element (k, v) in X,
the resulting RDD will either continue all pairs of k
and the pair (v, w) for w and Y or k and the pair (v, None)
if no elements in Y have k.
It'll also contain, for all elements (k, v) in Y,
all pairs k and the pair (v, w) for v and X
or k in the pair (None, w) if no elements in X have k.
So it's a little complicated.
Let's actually look at an example.
So here, we have one collection consisting of the pair a and 1
and b and 4 and a second collection consisting
of a and 2 and c and 8.
When we produce the full outer join,
we'll end up with a with the pair 1 and 2,
because a appears both in X and in Y.
We'll end up with the pair b and 4 along with None,
because b only appears in X with the value 4.
And then finally, we'll end up with the pair
c and the pair (None, 8), because c only
appears in Y and not in X, and it appears with the value 8.